<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="MS.9318">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title/>
            <title type="collection">Wellcome Collection</title>
            <respStmt xml:id="EC">
               <resp when="2022">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>Elena Carter</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="AP">
               <resp when="2023">Template</resp>
               <persName>Adrian Plau</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="WG">
               <resp when="2023">TEI Encoder</resp>
               <persName>Will Greenacre</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Wellcome Collection</publisher>
            <idno>UkLW</idno>
            <address>
               <orgName type="institution">Wellcome Collection</orgName>
               <street>215 Euston Rd</street>
               <settlement>London</settlement>
               <postCode>NW1 2BE</postCode>
            </address>
            <distributor>
               <email>library@wellcome.ac.uk</email>
            </distributor>
            <idno type="msID">MS.9318</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <settlement>London</settlement>
                  <institution>Wellcome Collection</institution>
                  <repository>Wellcome Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">MS9318</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="Sierra">
                     <idno>b33049506</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier type="accession">
                     <idno>2661</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <summary><p>WRIGHT, Thomas (c.1654 -?) Manuscript entitled "A Call to Repentance or a Warning before Judgement" [Circa. 1716. Dated on title page].</p>
                     <p> Thomas Wright recounts an unprovoked and seemingly mindless attack that he suffered 'in the year 1668' at the age of 14 and which left him disabled for the remainder of his life.</p>
                     <p> He issues a 'Warning before Judgement' to those who have done injury to him, and to encourage 'all wicked men to leave of their boasting and Glorying of their wicked and cruel actions and to call their sins to remembrance'. </p>
                     <p> Towards the end of his narrative, he describes the appalling attitudes of society towards him as a disabled man: 'I am become a scorn […] struck at me with their Cudgells others have struck me with their fists […] I am become now a prey unto the Children in the streets'. </p>
                     <p> He is continually confronted with the prevailing attitudes towards disability: 'I am made to hang down my head like a bullrush and to goe heavily […] like a sparrow on the houstop which hath no mate'.  </p>
                     <p> This first-hand account of disability in early modern England is written by Thomas Wright at the age of 62, 48 years after the incident. Written in an easy-to-read script, the Wright's account offers an articulate affecting encapsulation of one man's suffering. With biblical quotations throughout, this account also offers a warning to the parents of children to 'bring up your children in the fear of the Lord while they are young that so when they are old they may never depart from it' </p></summary>
                  <textLang mainLang="en">English</textLang>
                  <msItem n="" xml:id="MS_9318_1">
                     <author>Thomas Wright</author>
                     <title>"A Call for Repentance or a Warning before Judgment"</title>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="octavo">
                     <supportDesc material="vellum">
                        <support/>
                        <extent>30 leaves<dimensions unit="mm">
                              <dim type="diameter">95</dim>
                              <dim type="length">155</dim>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <collation>
                           <formula>Pagination [1, title], [1, blank], [3, introduction], [1, blank], 39, [15, blanks].</formula>
                        </collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote>Title page within slightly decorated border, text in a neat upright hand.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <additions>
                     <p>Several pen trials to later pages, title copied onto front paste-down in a less sophisticated hand.</p>
                  </additions>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding>
                        <p>Contemporary sheep, heavily rubbed and worn, front board has been re-attached using small pieces of material. Ownership inscription to rear endpaper: “Wm Masham Book”. Watermark: Pro Patria. </p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country>England</country>,
                     </origPlace>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian">c.1716</origDate>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>The seller purchased the manuscript from a dealer in Lincolnshire who had obtained the volume in a house clearance.</provenance>
                  <acquisition>Purchased from  Dean Cooke Rare Books Ltd, 2022.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p>Digitised in full</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2023-07-05">WG created xml file.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p> TRANSCRIPT: </p>
         <p> [typos, capitalisations and italics are those of the author] </p>
         <p> [p.1] </p>
         <p> To the Reader. </p>
         <p> It is the opinion of carnal and wicked men that when sin is committed done and past that they shall never be call'd to an account for the same; But (alas) no length of time can wear sin away it if be not taken away by true sincere and unfeigned repentance: It is said of David that after he had committed Adultry and murder that he slept securely in his sin for a season. But then the Lord sent his Prophet to a wake him out of his security to put him in mind of what he had done and to pronounce his judgements against him for the same hereby we may observe that men may commit many and great sins and offences and yet battle their consciences </p>
         <p> [p.2] </p>
         <p> And sleep securely in the same for a time but yet sin is so contrary to the nature and being of God that he will not suffer it to go unpunished tho it be committed never so secretly and by the choicest of his servants also hereby we may further observe the great mercy and goodness of God that he will not destroy a people or person but he will first send his messenger to put them in mind and reprove them for their sins before he sends his judgments to try them if they will repent. To this end I have written this little book as a friendly invitation or warning to all wicked men to leave of their boasting and Glorying of their wicked and cruel actions and to call their sins to remembrance and to humble themselves and repent for the same, that </p>
         <p> [p.3] </p>
         <p>  they may prevent Gods wrath and vengeance which hangs over their heads and will be shortly executed upon them, except they repent that wicked men may know that there is a God that revengeth the cause of the innocent (To me belongs vengeance and recompence their foot shall slide in due time, for the day of their calamity is at hand, and ihe things that shall come upon them make hast. Deut. 32, 35. </p>
         <p> [p.4] </p>
         <p> [pen marks across top as if testing the ink - these have bled onto the opposite page] </p>
         <p> 1 [p.5] </p>
         <p> [Title indecipherable due to ink staining from opposite page] </p>
         <p> Because pentance against an evil work is not executed speedily therefore the hearts of the Sons of men are fully set in them to do evil. </p>
         <p> From the first part of these words of scripture, we may observe the great mercy and goodness of God towards the sons of men in that he deterreth the time as not being willing to execute his Judgments speedily upon them for their evil doings because he desireth not the death or destruction of man but rather that he would repent forsake their sins and come to the knowledge of the Truth and be Saved. </p>
         <p> From the Latter part of these words we may also observe the bad  use too many men make of god's mercy and forbearance that is to harden themselves in their sins fully to set their hearts to do evil and resolvedly to run on in a sinfull course of life, as a hors rush into the battle. </p>
         <p> 2 [p.7] </p>
         <p> Without fear or dread until they have often ruined both themselves and others as we have daily too many examples to prove the truth hereof, one of which you have here following, an experimentall account of which I myself have received and suffered from the hands of this sort of men, and I desire it may be a sufficient example for all men to take warning by who act without the fear of God and without the true light and life of Grace. </p>
         <p> In the year 1668 on the eleventh day of August about the middle of the day and about the fourteenth year of my age as I was riding about my lawfull occasion to water my Father's Oxen there chanced to come that way a company of shearers amongst whom was a wicked man betwixt 25 and 30 years of age, who seeing me come at a distance did get a great hors or Gofs thistle and brought it in his hands behind him making hast before the rest of his company and casting to meet mee in the strait of the way, when I saw him I was greatly afraid of him because of his stern and cruell countenance tho' I saw no weapen therein; but for fear of him I shund the way as far as I could for the hedge and gave them the time of the day, but God knows he run out of his company to me and struck a great Gofs thistle which he had in  </p>
         <p> 3 [p.8] </p>
         <p> his hands behind him under my mares tail which caused her to give a great leap that caused my hat to fall of my head, which both he and his company say she holding still this Thistle so fast under her tail that it caused her to run so furiously [?] away with me so that I cryed </p>
         <p> 4 [p.9] </p>
         <p> Out in the Name of God and Jesus Christ to them to help me else I was slain. </p>
         <p> An old woman also in their company cryed out with me for Christ sake help him else he is slain and it was in their power to have helped me for my mare did run straight to his brother which was about two hundred yards behind him and I held out my halter and cryed out to him in the name and for the sake of Jesus Christ to take hold of it and save my life and limbs which he might easily have done but he willfully stept away and would not. But my mare continued running furiously down a steep hill till she tumbled over her head and broke my thigh bone in three pieces and her own leg which so lamed danted and amazed her that  </p>
         <p> 5 [p.10] </p>
         <p> She could not rise but she lay upon me till a little girl which was keeping of sheep came from the far side of the moor and raised her up. But in the riseing up my buttons being riped open with the force of the fall she trode upon my bare brest with her hinder foot which hath caused me a great deal of pain and misery. </p>
         <p> They sent a boy after me with my hat but he threw it upon the top of the hill and returned to them again. </p>
         <p> But so little regarded they what they had done what was become of me or whether I was alive or dead that they never asked the boy whether he saw me or no till they heard a report that I was slain. Then they asked the boy what he did with  </p>
         <p> 6 [p.11] </p>
         <p> My hat he replyed he saw me not and so he cast it upon the top of the hill. </p>
         <p> They they soposing I had been slain leaves of their work which was shearing of corn and goes home and takes in his hand such a like thistle thereby to act part of the Divel. John9.44. first to murther me and then to swear and lye that that was the thistle which they struck under my mares tail and that it fell from her and she went softly whilst she was in their sight whereas all the company that were with them saw and knew it to the contrary, also the deed testified the Truth of the sad and cruel action for the thistle the Mare's Halter and my shoe all which was pulled of with the fall lay by me and that all the people which  </p>
         <p> 7 [p.12] </p>
         <p> came thither to see me saw besides this Mare stood my Father to thirteen Nobles and she was so lamed with the fall that my father sold her to a poor man But for six shillings who I suppose knock'd her on the head for I never saw nor heard more of her whereas if she had gone softly she would not have lamed herself. </p>
         <p> And now let wise and Good men judg by all this what this man hath done to me and what I have suffered by him and not my self only but also my Father and Mother and all my Family for want of my help and succour which they cannot have because he hath destroyed my Health and Limbs, though by Gods mercy I was not murthered out at present yet he hath put me to a lingering and painfull </p>
         <p> 8 [p.13] </p>
         <p> Dath and now this man never repented or said he was sory for this wicked deed but on the contrary in my hearing amongst his companions hath made it his bost and his Glory to tell of his Cruel Actions to pleasure his hearers, forgetting that God is present at all times and in every place hearing the words and beholding the Actions of every man. But I greatly fear the Lord my God therefore have I never sought to take revenge of him myself though I have had full and sufficient power to have done it, For then should I have taken the Sword of justice out of the hands of my God who saith Vengeance is mine and I will repay Deuter. 32.35. Now this and some other men </p>
         <p> 9 [p.14] </p>
         <p> Saith this was but a misfortune which God had ordained to me before I was born and so he did nothing but what God had ordained should be done and therefore what needs he to repent or be sory for it and thus wicked men makes God the Author of their evil Actions to cleare themselves. </p>
         <p> And our Saviour Christ was foretold of his Father to come &amp; by all his Prophets from Adam even till he did come and Suffer those things which he suffered, so you may say of the persecutors and murtherers of Christ that they was but the instruments in the hand of God to bring his work to pass and do unto the Son of God what he had foretold should be done </p>
         <p> 10 [p.15] </p>
         <p> And come to pass, offences in deed must come but wo unto that man by whom they come  </p>
         <p> Matt: 18,7. </p>
         <p> For search and enquire what became of his persecutors and murtherers what became of Judas Pilate and Herod, and all those Jews who cryd crucifie him crucifie him let his blood be up on us and upon our children </p>
         <p> Matt: 27,25. </p>
         <p> God did revenge his blood upon them for the Romans came against them and burnt up their Citties destroyed their habitations slew their persons and dashed their children against the walls. </p>
         <p> Tho' our Saviour Christ forgave all his enemies and prayed to his Father to forgive them  </p>
         <p> 11 [p.16] yet I heard of none that obtained pardon but those that repented but some of his enimes would not and some of them could not repent, for saith he how often would I have gathered thy Children together as a hen gethereth her chickens under her wings and you would not Matt: 23,37. </p>
         <p> Judas and Pilate could not repent but their Conscience terrified them so that they had no peace where ever they fled, but they laid violent hands upon and slew themselves, Matth 27,5 </p>
         <p> Peace comes from God and rests in the hearts of Good men which receives and walks in the light and love of that peace, my peace I give unto you John, 14,27 </p>
         <p> Isaiah:32,27 </p>
         <p> Good men you hear have peace </p>
         <p> 12 [p.17] </p>
         <p> Inward peace with God which carries and supports them through all difficulties and dangers and bring them to the Kingdom of Everlasting peace and joy in the Holy Ghost. Rom,14,17. But there is no peace to the wicked. Isaiah,57,21. </p>
         <p> No cruel sinfull and wicked man can enter into this Kingdom or enjoy this peace. </p>
         <p> For the seed of this Kingdom which God hath sown in the Hearts of every man becomes in Good men the savour of life unto life, but in wicked men the savour of death unto death For tho' God hath  so loved us that he hath given his own  </p>
         <p> 13 [p.18] </p>
         <p> Son out of his Bosom to dye for us yet no man can be saved except he repent except ye repent ye shall all likewise perish. </p>
         <p> Luke, 13,3 and no man can repent when he will for to this end God hath exalted his Son to be a Prince and a Saviour to give repentance and remission of this Act:5,31. </p>
         <p> Therefore saith and repentance is the first steps to salvation Mar:16,16. Rev: 2,5. </p>
         <p> But what is Repentance it is not for wicked men they murther maim sear curs and lye and take Gods Name in vain or say or do any evil action it is not I say enough to say God forgive me or I have sinned. Mat:27,4. </p>
         <p> This Repentance proceeds but from the stings of their Conscience which they ever feel to prick them </p>
         <p> 14 [p.19] </p>
         <p> After their sin. </p>
         <p> Wicked men which never in all their life regarded God or Goodness but made a Scoff at it yet when they come to dye and feels death and judgment to approach upon them then if they have time they will cry out for fear of the same to God for help, for they know then as death leaves them judgment must find them and their mouths will be full of good words but this is no true repentance for hear what the righteous Judge will say unto them. Mat:7,28. For where now is the earnest 2 Cor, 1,22. 5,5. The Evidence and assurance of your Salvation 2 Peter 1,10 which you must have if you hope to b saved. Where now is the Evidence of a Good and  </p>
         <p> 15 [p.20] </p>
         <p> Godly life can you now say with good Hezekiah and say truly I beseech the O Lord remember now I have walked before thee in truth and with a perfect heart and have done that which is right in thy sight. 2 Kings,20,3. </p>
         <p> True repentance in a word is to cease to do evil and learn to do well. Isaiah 1,16,17. To do justly to love mercy and to walk humbly with God. </p>
         <p> Therefore now while you have time youth health and strength make it your chief business to labour to get your peace made with God and your assurance of eternall life by timely repentance forsaking of your sins and living in the full and sincere obedience to the commands of God that so you may surly say when you come to dye I beseech thee O Lord. </p>
         <p> 16 [p.21] </p>
         <p> Remember now how I have walked before thee in truth and with a perfect heart and have done that which is good in thy sight. 2 Kings: 20,3. Then you will find that your labour hath not been in vain in the Lord. 1. Corinth, 25,20. For then your death will be precious in the sight of the Lord. Psalms, 116,16. And after death you will hear that blessed and joyfull voice saying to you come ye blessed of my Father inherit the Kingdom prepared for you from the foundation of the world. </p>
         <p> Mathew 25,34. </p>
         <p> There is a time also of our calling to repentance which if we refuse may never be obtain'd again. The time is the present time to day faith  </p>
         <p> 17 [p.22] </p>
         <p> The Lord if ye will hear my voice harden not your hearts  </p>
         <p> Hebrews, 3,0. </p>
         <p> For some through the hardness of their hearth have refused the voice of their calling to repentance and after wards have sought it carefully with tears but have not found it. Othen to day whilst it is called today let us hearken to the voice of Christ who knocks and calls at the door of our hearts  let us prize time whilest it is time let us cast of the works of darkness and put on the armour of light. Romans 13,12. </p>
         <p> Let us walk honestly and work the works of God whilest it is day for the night comes when no man can walk or work John 9,4. I made hast saith David and made no delay to keep thy commandments. Psalm 119,63. </p>
         <p> Now if you will not forsake your sins for the love of God and Goodness yet forsake them for the  </p>
         <p> 18 [p.23] </p>
         <p> Love of your selves for consider the guilt of sin which you have felt what stings and pangs it leaves behind it upon your hearts and consciences which grieves and quenches the good spirit of God in you Eph,4,30. Which is the earnest of your salvation. Now if you will not forsake your sins in time they will bring you to death for by sin came death and the stings of death is sin and after death they will bring you to judgment where you will hear that sad sentence of your judge wh would have been your saviour depart from me cursed into everlasting fire prepared for the Devil and his Angells to all eternity from whence there is no redemption for ever Mat:25,45. </p>
         <p> And now as I have said before Faith and repentance is the first steps to salvation but by faith here is not to be understood a dead faith james, 2,37,26. But a living and a working faith 2 Peter,1,5,6,7. For every one that truly believes they </p>
         <p> 19 [p.24] </p>
         <p> Be saved Mark 16,16. </p>
         <p> And as here the promise of Salvation is made to the true believers in Christ to search all Gods promises which he hath made unto us in Scripture and you will find they are all made upon a condition and if the condition be fulfilled on our part he is faithfull that hath promised. Hebrews 10,23. Who will not fail but will certainly perform his promises made to every condition, therefore believe repent and humble your selves before the Lord that so you may prevent God's Judgements pronounced against you see Ahab,1 Kings 21,29 and the Ninivites Jonah 3,10. God resisteth the proud but gives grace to the humble and what shall I say awake thou that sleepeth Eph:5,14. Make hast and come unto Christ now when he calls come unto me all ye that are heavy laden and I will give you rest Mat,11,20 </p>
         <p> For he is the teacher of his people </p>
         <p> 20 [p.25] </p>
         <p> Himself first he teacheth them by his word. John 15,14 </p>
         <p> Secondly he teacheth them by his Spirit, John 14,26 </p>
         <p> Thirdly he teacheth them by his example. Mat 11,29. He is the way the Truth and the life. John 14,6. He is the good Sheppard of his sheep and the door into the sheepfold. John 10,9,11. He is the true light that enlightens every man that cometh into the world. John, 11,1,9. </p>
         <p> He is the good Seedsman which hath sown the good seed of the Kingdom in the hearts of every man. Mat 13,37. The Kingdom of God is within you saith he. Luke17,21. And it is like a grain of mustard seed. Mathew, 13,31. And it consisteth in righteousness peace and joy in the holy Ghost. Rom: 14,17. Which Kingdom if we be not a pertaker of here we shall never be a pertaker of it hereafter. I say if we be not a pertaker of the Kingdom of  </p>
         <p> 21 [p.26] </p>
         <p> Grace here we must never be a pertaker of the Kingdom of Glory hereafter, how ever wicked men may flatter themselves and say they are Christians and God is mercyfull and Christ dyed for the sins of all men and they hope to be saved and go to heaven as well as the best tho' they neither walk nor work Io,9,4. </p>
         <p> But this is an uncertain foundation which is built upon the sand. Mat 7,26. Which (if they live and dye int heir sins) will besure to fail them for except ye repent ye shall all perish. Luke 13,3. For except a man be born again he cannot enter into the Kingdom of God for flesh and blood cannot inherit the Kingdom of God neither can corrupton inherit incorruption. Corinth, 15,50. For heaven is a place of purity where no unclean thing can come. 1.Cor:6,9,10. Rev: 22,15. Eph: 5,5. But suppose a wicked man should be snatch'd away and carry'd into heaven how unsuitable would that place be unto him for heaven is </p>
         <p> 22 [p.27] </p>
         <p> An unholy place there is an holy God there is the Son of God which is holy there is the holy Angels and there is the spirits of just men made perfect their work there is to rejoice and sing praises to God which sits upon the throne and the lambe for ever. Rev.5,12,13. </p>
         <p> Now how disagreeable would this place this Company this work be to an unregenerate and and wicked man, he would be like a fish out of his element, therefore follow peace with all men and holiness without which no man can see the Lord. Heb,12,14. </p>
         <p> Hath not God made man upright after his own image placed him a little lower then the Angels endured him with sence and reason, wisdom and understanding whereby he is enabled to discern betwixt good and evil but man by his own will and disobedience diverts him self from God the chief Good turns himself to that which is evil and  </p>
         <p> 23 [p.28] </p>
         <p> there by runs the hazard of so great and invaluable a loss as the loss of the peace of his conscience the love and favour of God the eternall salvation of his pretious and immortall soul and all for the enjoyment of the uncertain pleasure of sin for so short a moment of time and yet men who hath hardened themselves in their sins whose hearts are fully set in them to do evill do take such delight and pleasure therein that it is as hard for these men to cease to do evill and learn to do well as it is for the Ethiopian to change his skin or the Leopard his spots. Jeram:13,23. Wicked men that is brought up in the custom and practice of an evill and wicked life will not be recaim'd tho' one should rise from the dead to admonish and warn them of their destruction. Luke, 16,31. </p>
         <p> For they believe not Gods word they despise his Commands they regard not his promises nor fear his judgment but they will live in the </p>
         <p> 24 [p.29] </p>
         <p> Practice of a wicked life never considering or regarding their latter end till they come to dye and have no more time but to fetch or expire in their last groans then when they feel within themselves the terrours and cryes of their own guilty consciences which accuses them for all their sinfull wicked and cruel actions of their lives then how will their hearts which hath been so stubborn and rebellious against God and man be filled with fear and dread and horror now saith the sinner if I had all the world I would give it for the peace of my conscience the love and favour of God and the Salvation of my pretious soul all which I have had often offered me by the motions of the Spirit of truth by the Gospell of Jesus Christ and the ministers there of freely without money and without price but I would not except of it. I would not believe and come unto Jesus </p>
         <p> 25 [p.30] </p>
         <p> Christ for life but now whither shall I go or to whom shall I fly for help If I call to my companions which so often I have made merry with my words and actions there is no hel in them but agrevate my misries and if I call to my friends they cannot help me Silver and Gold is of no value. If I call to the Rocks and to the Mountains to fall up on me and cover me they can not chide me from the fierce wrath of the Lord who I have so much offended, alas alas what shall I do I cannot live nor I dare not dye and whither I am going I cannot tell, thus men in health rejects and casts of their Creator and God of all mercies spends their most precious time in vanity and ends their days in misries from whence we </p>
         <p> 26 [p.31] </p>
         <p> May observe what a sad thing it is for men to live in sin and put of their repentance from day to day saying they will repent tomorrow may be the day of their death, nay they know not but this night their souls may be required of them and then their thoughts perish so they that will not know God now in the days of mercy must certainly know him hereafter in justice and judgment for it is appointed for all men once to dye and after that to appear in Judgment where every man must be justified or condemned according as his works hath been good or bad. Mat:25,31 to the end of the Chap. </p>
         <p> And now my advice to all Parents as you tender your duty towards God the peace of your Conscience the everlasting </p>
         <p> 27 [p.32] </p>
         <p> Comfort peace and Salvation of your own and the Souls of your children take care nay I say let it be your chiefest care to educate and bring up your children in the fear of the Lord while they are young that so when they are old they may never depart from it. Prov:22,6. </p>
         <p> As good and Godly parents ever takes care to instruct their children and families in those things which tends to the glory of God the comfort and happiness of their Souls and bodys both here and here after. Gen:13,19. So foolish wicked and ungodly parents as they live themselves so they train up their children like bruits even like the horse and the mule which have neither guide nor government Psalms32,9. Wherefore they are a dishonour to God a shame to their parents injurious and </p>
         <p> 28 [p.33] </p>
         <p> Often ruinous to their neighbours for they delight themselves in mischief and glory in their own shame but the fear of the Lord is the chiefest wisdom and to depart from evil the gretest understanding Job,28,28. </p>
         <p> Now had this man feared God he would have suffered me to have passed peacibly by him and not have run out of his way to have maim me and my mare and broken my bones asunder and brought God's judgment upon his own head when I gave him no occasion but the Fear of God was not in all his thoughts, but here may see the fruits of wicked men which in scripture are termed Devils Dogs Beasts and Swine and the like. John 6,70. Mathew 7,6. I Cor,15,32. </p>
         <p> 29 [p.34] </p>
         <p> Rev 22,25. </p>
         <p> From such can be expected no better fruit for do men gether grapes of thorns or figs of thistle a good tree cannot bring forth evil fruit neither can a corrupt tree bring forth good fruit but every tree is known by it's fruit. Mat:7,16. There fore all parents that fear God as it is your Duty to let it be your care to pray night and day to God for your children to give them a portion of his heavenly grace and holy spirit which is better then all the riches you can provide for them and that God may bless them in their rising up and in their lying down in their going forth and in their coming in and that God may bless preserve and keep them out of the hands and power of </p>
         <p> 30 [p.35] </p>
         <p> Wicked, cruel and merciless men which fear not God for the tender mercies of these men are cruel Proverbs.12:10. Wicked men are not only the ruine of their own souls and bodys but they are the ruine and distruction of nations countrys and Kingdoms cities towns and places where they dwell was it notfor the sins and wickeness of those men that God destroyed the old world Gen:6. Was it not for the sins and wickedness of the people that dwelled therein that God destroyed the Cityes of Sodom and Gomorrah. Gen:19. Wicked men are so odious in the sight of the Lord that he hath caused the earth to open her mouth and swallow them up quick. Num:16,31,32. Have we not many such like </p>
         <p> [31 though not numbered] [p.36] </p>
         <p> Examples of the overthro and distruction of wicked men. Oh! Then let us fear and tremble before the Lord and the power of his might for as he is a God gratious and mercifull slow to anger and of great kindness to them that love him and keep his commandments so he is a severe and just judge to his enemies and to them that hate him for they shall be before him as Chaff before the wind or as Stubble before the fire for if the righteous can scarcly be saved where shall the ungodly and sinners appear. Peter 4,19. And if many shall seek to enter in at the strait gate and shall not be able what shall those do which never [gap - faint word upon?] seek or strive att all. Luke 13,24. </p>
         <p> 32 [p.37] </p>
         <p> Consider these things and remember your latter end Deu.32,29. Beleive repent and turn unto the Lord in time that you may be saved. For as I live saith the Lord God I have no pleasure in the death of the wicked but that the wicked turn from his way and live. Ezek,33,11. </p>
         <p> Reader do not think I have written these lines out of envie or malice to my enime or enemies for I freely forgive all mine enemies but I have written them but I have written them out of love to them that he or they may remember what they have done and repent and be saved. And though the fool hath said in his heart there is no God. Psalm.14,3. Yet let not wicked men make a mock of these things for they will find there is a God that will not nor cannot be mocked for what soever a man sowes that shall </p>
         <p> 33 [p.38] </p>
         <p> He reap Galations 6,7. </p>
         <p> And now my freinds I desire you all to remember this act of cruely done to me yet not so as to take any revenge for it but to take warning by it so that you may never use any manner of cruelty either to man or beat neither your own nor others in publick nor in private for the eyes of the Lord are in every place beholding the evil and the good. Prov:15,3. </p>
         <p> For he hath made all creatures for our use but not for our abuse and though he bear long and suffer much yet will he remember every cruel action done to his creatures and in due time he will revenge their cause therefore take heed that you do not forget God in your hearts or say he delayes his coming and so begin to smite and abuse his creatures which are your brethren and fellow servants least he </p>
         <p> 34 [p.39] </p>
         <p> Who is the Lord of these servants come in an hour when you think not of and cut you asunder and appoint you your portion with Hypocrites there shall be weeping and gnashing of teeth Mat:24,45,53. </p>
         <p> For what measure you meet to others shall be measured to you again. Luke 6,38 </p>
         <p> For as he hath promised to reward the secrets works of piety Mat,6,6 so he hath promised to punish the secret works of impiety  2 Sam.12,11,12. </p>
         <p> For nothing is secret that shall not be made manifest neither anything hid that shall not be known and come abroad. Luke 5,17.Mat 30,26,27. Therefore as you hope to find mercy from and in the sight of the Lord be ye mercy full as your heavenly Father is mercyfull. Luke 6,36. Mat 5,7. </p>
         <p> 35 [p.40] </p>
         <p> For with the mercyfull the Lord will shew himself mercyfull and with the upright marche will shew himself upright and with the pure he will shew himself pure and with the froward he will shew himself unsavorie 2. Sam:22,26,27. </p>
         <p> See then that ye walk circumspectly not as fools but as wise redeeming the time because the days are evill. Eph:5,35,16. </p>
         <p> And consider and let all that read this book consider and take warning hereby I say consider what this desperate act of cruelty hath done to me and not to me only but to my parents also who brought me up with care and pains to the age of fourteen years at which age I was healthfull and strong exceeding most of my age I was willing carefull and industrious in my fathers business which was a joy and comfort to my parents but now </p>
         <p> 36 [[.41] </p>
         <p> By this deed their joy was turn'd into sorrow lamentations and mourning for me and that not for a day but all the time of their life. For now I should have been a help to my parents but now I am become a greater care and charge to them then ever I was before and that without recovery for now I can not help my self but am forced to go upon crutches all the time of my life to support my body I might have been helpful and serviceable in my generation to my Relations town and Country but now I am become a charge and burthen to all I might have lived in the society esteem and favour of men but now I am become a scorn and derision to all some men now out of scorn as I have passed by them have struck at me with their cudgels others have struck me with their fists and made me to reel others out of scorn have waged their heads and put forth their tongues at me. I am become </p>
         <p> 37 [p.42] </p>
         <p> Now a prey unto the children in the streets who have followed me by companies making their sport of me abusing and calling me wors then the worst of creatures in a word I am made to hang down my head like a bullrush and to goe heavily I mourn as a dove and chatter as a crane of the Wilderness. I am like an owl of the desert and like a sparrow on the housetop which hath no mate. </p>
         <p> Have mercy upon me O Lord for I am in trouble mine eyes are consumed with grief yea my soul is troubled my heart faileth and my bones are consumed, I was a reproach among my neighbours and a fear to mine acquaintance they that did see me without fled from me. I am forgotten as a dead man out of mind. I am like a broken vessel for I have heard the slander of many fears was on every side while they took councell against me they divised to take away my life. </p>
         <p> But I trusted in thee O Lord I said </p>
         <p> 38 [p.43] </p>
         <p> Thou are my God. </p>
         <p> My tunes are in thy hands deliver me from the hands of mine enemies and from them that persecute me. </p>
         <p> Make thy face to shine upon thy servant save me for thy mercys sake. </p>
         <p> And give me I beseech thee such a measure of thy heavenly grace and holy Spirit as may be sufficient to support me through all the dangers and difficulties of this life so that nothing may be able to separate me from the love of thee my God and that I may not suffer ony as a man but that I may suffer as a Christian that so being a pertaker of the sufferings of thy dear Son here I may also be made a pertaker of his Glory here after and that I may see thy face in the land of the </p>
         <p> 39 [p.44] </p>
         <p> Righteous where with them even thy redeemed ones I may sing praises to thee my God who siteth upon the Throne and to the Lambe for ever; and this I beg for thy name for thy mercy and for the merits and sake of thy dear Son Jesus Christ to whom with thee and the Holy Ghost be all honour and Glory from me and every Creature for ever and ever. </p>
         <p> Amen. </p>
         <p> p.51 </p>
         <p> Mr [?] Masham Book </p>
         <p> Inset of end binding: </p>
         <p> Some pencil annotations incl 'Gill' and what appears to be a sum. </p>
         <p> [some pencil shorthand? Annotations below] </p>
         <p> [pages continue to be numbered though blank - pages 47-54 bear ink scribbles as if the author is testing his pen out; the final page, p.54  has a column with lines and further scribbles.] </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
