<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng"
            type="application/xml"
            schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
        ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="MS_144">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>MS_144</title>
        <title type="collection">Wellcome Collection</title>
        <respStmt xml:id="SM">
          <resp when="1973">Cataloguer</resp>
          <persName>S. A. J. Moorat</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt xml:id="RM">
          <resp when="2002-10-08">Calm encoder</resp>
          <persName>Macfarlr</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Wellcome Collection</publisher>
        <idno>UkLW</idno>
        <address>
          <orgName>Wellcome Collection</orgName>
          <street>215 Euston Rd</street>
          <settlement>London</settlement>
          <postCode>NW1 2BE</postCode>
        </address>
        <distributor>
          <email>library@wellcome.org</email>
        </distributor>
        <idno type="msID">MS.144</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <country>United Kingdom</country>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <institution>Wellcome Collection</institution>
            <repository>Wellcome Library</repository>
            <idno type="shelfmark">MS.144</idno>
            <altIdentifier type="CalmRef">
              <idno>MS144</idno>
            </altIdentifier>
            <altIdentifier type="accession">
              <idno>75684</idno>
            </altIdentifier>
            <altIdentifier type="previous">
              <idno/>
            </altIdentifier>
            <altIdentifier type="CalmID">
              <idno>5fd92d4e-fe5e-4367-b21d-d0209ccedc58</idno>
            </altIdentifier>
            <altIdentifier type="Sierra">
              <idno>b19258124</idno>
            </altIdentifier>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>[p]A collection of medical, cookery and veterinary receipt, etc. : mainly by two hands, one c. 1650, the other dated 1731-1739.[/p]
[p]The original hand is that of ff. 1-82, of which ff. 1-38 are cookery receipts and the remainder medical. It also appears on 7 pp. at the end, containing veterinary receipts. At the end also are 11 pp. headed 'Dialectica est ars bene disserendi', partly in English and partly in Latin, by a different hand, also c. 1650.[/p]
[p]Comprises the following recipes:  Booke of receites howe to make a sweet cake For a potle of wine epecres Perfumed pufes; To preserve quinces To make marmelet; To preserve whit bulles or whit peare plomes To preserve barberys; To preserve aprecottes To preserve cheryes; To preserve goosbeery Losenges of roses or flowers; To preserve oranges and leamonds; Sirope of Fimetary Sirrope of vilolets; Sirope of clowgile flowers Sirope of rasberyes Sirope of orrenges ore Lemonds; To make mannes cristi; To make allmond Butter To make whit leach; To make allmond flurerdeles For a heghoge puden; Howe to make a lumber pye Sawse for a shoulder of mutton; Sause for a shoulder of moton To rost a shoulder of moton To make sturgon of a tarkey A stued lobster; Frid harty chocke A fremhe dishe A fremh dishe A fride rabett Sause of anchoves; Smaulde Sooles Frid chichens To peckelle oysters; For a boore; To make fine crackell cakes Mis killegrew cakes; To make gingerbread of allmonds; To make very fine Biscute; To make Hydromel To make mead; To make rosa solis or ros solis; To make treacle of herbes For a coold stomacke cowld An electuarie against malamolie; To stanche blood when the vaine is cutt Another of ##r Groopes Another To stanche bleden att the nose Another Another; For the ruketts A drinke for the same; Sirrup for the Rickets For the scurvie a excellent dreinke; A receipt for the scurvy Another For the rickets For convoltion fitts in a child Good for the nurce; To prevent convoltion fitts For convoltion fitts A electuary good for convoltion fitts; To make one to sleape For the rickets and consumtion; Medicine against the pectilence taught King Henry the Seventh King Henry the Eight sent this to the Lord Mayor of London against the plague, cont. on folio 52; cont. from folio 51, King Henry the eight sent this to the Lord Mayor of London against the plague For the plague in the guts in man; For a tetter To skine a sore For a canker in the mouth Another Another For a straine or wrince For a cutt or green wound; For the paulsies in the hands; For paine in the backe Another; For spitting of blood For any in the stomacke or infecttions truble For the ianndice Another for the yellow jaundice; To cause one to sleep For the stone collick For the worms; For paine in the teethe For a sweet breath A faire purgation; For the dropsce Another Good for the swelling in the body and leggs For the blood clenesing after the measels or sprenge off scabes, cont. on folio 60; cont. from folio 59, To bring out the smale pox or measells A great secret secret to cure a cough in 2 or 3 days A precious watter for the eyes; A perfect and a proved good water to take away the spotts of the smalepoxe; To make the face clean and fair and take awaye spottsFor the smale poxe and to bring them out; For the patient that have the small poxe Electuary against looseneffe Another for looseneffe and a could stomake For the smale pox or swine pocks to bring them out To cause one to sleep To cause one to sleepe; A very good broath to comfort stomack and nurithe the body; For the wind of mother and convoltions fitts For one thats trubled with winde and fleme; Most soueraine for wind; A very good water against Melamholy, cont. on folio 67; cont. from folio 66, A very good water against Melamholy; To still aqua vite To make the best aqua composite A very good aqua coposita to bee mixed with rosasolis cordiall and comfortable; Dotter Stenens water named aqua mirabila Surfi# water to take att any time and after meales if anythinge afend the stomack; Dockter Butlers cordiall; For one that have a feveresh distemper; Lucatellus oyntment or balsamum Admirable for wounds; The vertues of Lucatellus oyntment or balsamum; A receite to keep a bruse from gangren never failem; To make the splene plaster in May; Pills for the stomack The spleene pills Creame of tarter one ounce For the splene; A receipt for the grene sickenesse The electuarie for the greene sickenesse, cont. on folio 87; The Third day purge A powder for the winde; A receipt an excellent to cause the to bee loose and have constant stoles; Pills for the stomake; For a stufeing in the stomacke; A diett drinke to cleanse the Blood and stomack; For a Ruhms or Soreness in the Eyes To Pickel Cucumbers and French Beans; A Receipt to make chesecakes; To pickel French Beans; To Make Currant Wine To make a Burning Ointmet To Make Green Goosebury wines To make Cherry Marmalett; To Make Mead that Drinks like Sherry Another To Make Mead; A Receipt for the Dropsy and scurvey prescribed by Docts Brosen of Norwich To Pickel Walnuts Like Mangoes; A Receipt for Dressing of fish A Receipt to Make Mead, cont. on folio 103; A Receipt to Make Mead To Make ginger bread; Fricaoie of Rabits; To Make Elder Wine; To Make a Cake; For a Cough For a Cough; Cordiall Bitters To make a Rabbit pye; Cordiall bitters For a Consumption or Dropsye Of milk Drink for a Hecktick fever Me Shermans Purge; To Make Lemon Brandy To make alamode Beef; To Collar Eles To make a Sack-posset; To make Barly Cream To make Jellys To make an orange pudding; To make a Triggary of Chickens or Rabbittes To make Cows-lip-Wine; To make a Karrot-pudding To make Scotch Collops; To Stew a Carp To pott a Hare Mead that was made for ### Doro Styleman February 1731 A #e#t to cure the Biting of a mad-Dog; To make almond [illegible] by Dr Hoiomans order To make a brown Bread pudding; A Marrow Pudding A rectfet for pain in the stomack; A Full discovery of the Medicines given by Ms Joanna Stevens for Cure of the stone and gravel The powder is thus prepar'd; The pills ar thus prepared; The Method of giving these Medicines are as follows; An approved receipt for the Cure or prevention of the Murrain in Cattle To Make a cake Lemon Pudding Lemon Cream; To Make a Rice Pudding To Make a Bread Pudding To make Minie pyes; To make Water Vinegar To make spice cakes To pickle Mushrooms; To make Catchup To make red Marmalade of Quinces; A Recipe for making Hessian Soup; For a felon; Dialectica ese ars bine differsndi; Bene; Eodemg# Sirsu logica dicta est Inventio est prima pars Bialectica de invemendis argumentis &amp;c # Inuentio est Pars Bialectica Prima De argumentis; Inrimendis Argumentu est quodad aliquid argumendu est affectum est etc Quod Affectum est Ad Arguendu Aliquid Ratio est in omnibus; Actus est in omnibusExistentia est in omnibusTime non existit nisi in veTime non potest separati a rebusQuales sant singula rationes sold st#se #sideratasinguld rationes affect## sunt ad argumenduGoldPer seArgumentu est artificiale and in artificiale; Artificiale prius in artificialeArgu artificiale estQuod ex se arguitArtif est primu vel a primo or#l#; cont. from folio 134, Artif est prima vel a primo or#l# Prima est Quod est sud originis Prima # artif originale ue# primogenea Primum es absolution aut comparatam Prima absoluta # Quod absolute a#gui#; A drinke for a sicke horse To prevent the murrain; For any straine or stiffeling of a horse For a horse that have Scaby heeles For the gravelling of a horse in the foot For the murrain in cows # and in and such catle To prevent the murrain For the murrain in pigs; For the could in the lungs or stomack of a horse For a horse that is broken winded For the farcy or by some called the farcion in a horse For a strain in the pastorn ioyut; For the plague in the guts of horses For the staggers and yellows For the scratches For the bots For bots and worms[/p]</summary>
            <textLang mainLang="" source="IANA">English</textLang>
            <msItem n="1" xml:id="MS_144_1">
              <author/>
              <title type="original">Book of receites, A</title>
              <title type="standard"/>
              <textLang mainLang="" source="IANA">English</textLang>
              <textLang mainLang="" source="IANA">Latin</textLang>
              <filiation/>
              <filiation>Hashmarks (#) in the summary of recipes are used to indicate where the indexers were unable to read the original text.</filiation>
            </msItem>
          </msContents>
          <physDesc>
            <objectDesc form="codex">
              <supportDesc material="">1 volume<extent>7 bl ll. + 87 ff. + 26 ll. + 97 bl. ll. + 5 bl. ll. 8vo. 16 x 11 cm. Original vellum gilt binding defective, both clasps wanting. A number of leaves have been cut out.<dimensions type="leaf" unit="cm"><dim type="width"/><dim type="length"/></dimensions><dimensions type="written" unit="cm"><dim type="width"/><dim type="length"/></dimensions></extent><foliation/><collation/><condition><p/><p/><p/><p/></condition><support><watermark/></support></supportDesc>
              <layoutDesc>
                <layout writtenLines="">
                  <note/>
                </layout>
              </layoutDesc>
            </objectDesc>
            <handDesc>
              <handNote script=""/>
            </handDesc>
            <decoDesc>
              <decoNote type="marginal"/>
              <decoNote type="illustration"/>
            </decoDesc>
            <additions/>
            <bindingDesc>
              <binding>
                <p>7 bl ll. + 87 ff. + 26 ll. + 97 bl. ll. + 5 bl. ll. 8vo. 16 x 11 cm. Original vellum gilt binding defective, both clasps wanting. A number of leaves have been cut out.</p>
              </binding>
            </bindingDesc>
          </physDesc>
          <history>
            <origin>
              <origDate>c.1650-1739</origDate>
            </origin>
            <provenance/>
            <acquisition>Purchased 1931.</acquisition>
            <acquisition type="accrual"/>
          </history>
          <additional>
            <adminInfo>
              <recordHist>
                <source>
                  <bibl>
                    <title>Catalogue of Western Manuscripts on Medicine and Science in the Wellcome Historical Medical Library</title>
                    <author>S. A. J. Moorat</author>
                    <placeName>London</placeName>
                    <publisher>Wellcome Institute for the History of Medicine</publisher>
                    <date>1962-1973</date>
                  </bibl>
                </source>
              </recordHist>
              <availability status="">
                <p/>
              </availability>
              <availability>
                <licence/>
              </availability>
              <custodialHist>
                <custEvent type="cataloguing">Database description transcribed from S.A.J. Moorat, [i]Catalogue of Western Manuscripts on Medicine and Science in the Wellcome Historical Medical Library[/i] (London: Wellcome Institute for the History of Medicine, 1962-1973).</custEvent>
                <custEvent type="exhibition"/>
                <custEvent type="digitised">Digitised: </custEvent>
              </custodialHist>
            </adminInfo>
            <surrogates>In addition, a microfilm copy is held as AMS/MF/232.</surrogates>
            <surrogates/>
            <listBibl>
              <bibl>Published (in microfilm form) in [i]Women in Medicine: Remedy Books, 1533 - 1865[/i], ed. Sara Pennell (Woodbridge, Connecticut: Primary Source Microfilm, 2004).</bibl>
            </listBibl>
            <listBibl>
              <bibl/>
            </listBibl>
          </additional>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="LCSH">
          <bibl>
            <ref target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/about.html#lcsh">Library of Congress Subject Headings</ref>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="MeSH">
          <bibl>
            <ref target="">MeSH</ref>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#LCSH">
          <list>
            <item facs="">
              <term ref="subject_">
                <p>[p]Rhetoric</p>
              </term>
            </item>
            <item facs="">
              <term ref="subject_">
                <p>[p]Formulas, recipes, etc.</p>
              </term>
            </item>
            <item facs="">
              <term ref="subject_">
                <p>Veterinary Medicine</p>
              </term>
            </item>
            <item facs="">
              <term ref="subject_">
                <p>Cooking</p>
              </term>
            </item>
            <item facs="">
              <term ref="subject_">
                <p>Medicine, Traditional</p>
              </term>
            </item>
            <item facs="">
              <term ref="subject_">
                <p>[p]Formulas, recipes, etc.</p>
              </term>
            </item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="#MeSH">
          <list>
            <item facs="">
              <term ref="subject_"/>
            </item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2026-05-05" who="Victoria Sloyan">Transformed Calm xml export to TEI xml file using a transformation scenario</change>
      <change when="" who="">Manual edits following automated Calm-TEI transformation</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
