<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng"
            type="application/xml"
            schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
        ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="MS_212">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>MS_212</title>
        <title type="collection">Wellcome Collection</title>
        <respStmt xml:id="SM">
          <resp when="1973">Cataloguer</resp>
          <persName>S. A. J. Moorat</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt xml:id="RM">
          <resp when="2002-10-08">Calm encoder</resp>
          <persName>Macfarlr</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Wellcome Collection</publisher>
        <idno>UkLW</idno>
        <address>
          <orgName>Wellcome Collection</orgName>
          <street>215 Euston Rd</street>
          <settlement>London</settlement>
          <postCode>NW1 2BE</postCode>
        </address>
        <distributor>
          <email>library@wellcome.org</email>
        </distributor>
        <idno type="msID">MS.212</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <country>United Kingdom</country>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <institution>Wellcome Collection</institution>
            <repository>Wellcome Library</repository>
            <idno type="shelfmark">MS.212</idno>
            <altIdentifier type="CalmRef">
              <idno>MS212</idno>
            </altIdentifier>
            <altIdentifier type="accession">
              <idno>19760</idno>
            </altIdentifier>
            <altIdentifier type="previous">
              <idno/>
            </altIdentifier>
            <altIdentifier type="CalmID">
              <idno>e931ffa6-22cf-4645-9c77-f705ddd33678</idno>
            </altIdentifier>
            <altIdentifier type="Sierra">
              <idno>b18749859</idno>
            </altIdentifier>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary>[p]Collection of medical receipts: in English, with some additions by other 17th cent. hands. 
[p]The orginal collection contains 342 numbered receipts: the Compiler's name is in the lower margin of the first leaf of text. There are 3 leaves of slightly smaller format added at the end with receipts by different hands. There are also additional receipts in the main body of the work, one of which is dated 1672.[/p]
[p]The volume begins with an alphabetical table of the recipts followed by the following entries: The usuall Wa#ckets with their figures; The composition of ye golden Paulsey water. Dr Matt; An other palsy water for the poorer sort allso excedinly tryed. Dr Matt To make Lucatasacs Ballsom; For an Ague For an Ague For an Ague For an Ague For a certain Ague For an Ague; For the Spleene To Procuer Sleepe A good barly water for all deseases of the Loungues For the head ache; For the Deafnes in hearing For the deafnes in hearing For the deafnes or Ousinger in the head For A Pluriscee For A Pluriscee; A powder For ye greene Sicknes For the greene Sicknes For a Cough of Lungs though the deseas Flash brought ye party to a grat weaknes For a bruis in the Eye To stope ye Laske For ane yt cannot hold theire water; For a Horcenes A medicen or bath for Dropece The Philosiphers Egge Ballsom of Ragworth. Dr Matt; A Very good Cooling glister. Dr Matt To heale a Sore nipple. Dr Matt A Speciall Caudle for the backe For a pinne or web in the Eye. This recepte proveth by Mis Morison For a impenye or swelled belly To stope the weeping sinewes; A Cordiall water good a gains any infeccious disease, As the plague, pox, measles or pestilent, burning feauer or to remoe any offencive or venimous mater from the hart or stomacke or to be used after a surfeit or in passions of the mother or for children in fitts of convosion, or is generally good to comfort &amp; stranthen Natur in all Gould causes what so Ever. Dr Matt To take away Warts; The Lady Dutches her Recett For Consumption Cough For a Cough if itt come ta a Consumption of the Longes To make sirrop of Turnips It is excellent for a Cough; The Composition of the powder for the Winde called, Pulvis Regis exceeding good for all Rumes &amp; Crud#ty in the stomacke &amp; all windes in the body bringeth lost appetites a gaine Comforteth the hart, brane &amp; sperrits Bringeth a gaine Lost Coller. Dr Matt To helpe the Pallet of the mouth falen A Posset drinke for the Stone For the Dropsie purgin of Fleame or water; To make a dyet drinke for the Liver By Dor Smith for Lettis Corbett A Speciall good salve upon any suddaine Occasion for any green wounde For a timpany or any swelling that Riseth with out anguish a bout the head or Necke like to wens A Cordill; To Make a Cordiall Water An Exelent modeate Cordiall to Drive out ye smalle Pox or ye like infection A Julipe; The Making of ye Cephallicall water; To Make a seare Cloath for ye faice; To Make Juyce of Liquores To Make a water for sore Eyes; The Recipt of ye Lady Staffords Pomatum Doctor Theams Resiet for the Gout The Lady Pulteng Recipt; To make biskitts of any sorte of frute To make Cowslip Wine; To Make an exllent Bath for Lame limbs of weake Children or oulder people For Bleard Eys; An Exelent Tri#ane; An oyntment for aches, Crampes, Stiches, straines, Sciatica, Strething of Sinewes, swelling of wounds and Brewses For the stone; The Ese of ye oynt ment for Aches To take a phylme offe an eye Coming by ye small pox or any Like Cause A wounde Water; To Make ye angell salve it is a spetiall good for bruisses &amp; to draw out thornes &amp; shivers of bones &amp; mixed with other fitt medicens it is good for many wounds &amp; sores A blacke Salve; To distill Corne Rose water for a Surffett; To Make the weapon Salve [initials Dr. D] For a pearle in ye Eye; A Speatiall greene Salve for Sores and gunshots To Make a Salve good for any Sore; An Exelent plasster for all wounds sores and aches To Make a medisen for A fellon; A Saule for all sores Called ye fles The order of dystilling hearbs wth Leaven salt yeast Creame or tartury; To Candy Angelica Stalkes To Breake a fellon &amp; heale it or for a plague sore To dye stilled water Red To strenthen a weake Stomacke To Give rest; Pills to take an Eower before supper to helpe degestion &amp; ye greene sicknes For a bruise in ye Eye For an old oosing sore yt will not heale with salve. Dr Matt; To Make Eypoeras. Dr Matt To Make Gallons of Eypoers. ha: Jamon: To Make one gather fleack; The Composition of ye water of Oringe Flowers; good for old weeping Sores. Dr Matt For a burne or scald A poultis for a sore brest; A poultis for to breake a brest or any swelling wch gathereth to a head A saule for a broken brest For ye swelling of ye Leges or Ague A healing Salve; The glister for timpeny The Fomentation To Make Esque Batth; An other palsy water of Exceding greate vertue in palesies, dissines of ye head &amp; weakenes of ye Sinnews. Dr. Matt A spetiall poutis for wounds or sores; Tincture of savory spetiall good for ye winde Collicke Rawnes of ye stomacke ye Kidneys and Mother. Dr Matt The Tinture of Savory An Electuary against ye Scorvey; Electuary of sassafras precious in all stoping of ye Liber, spleene Raine &amp; stomacke good for windines to Comfort digestion Expelleth Crude windy &amp; watery humors preserveth healthe &amp; procuerth a good Colour. Dr Matt The sassafras of Beare; A Cordiall water good against any infeccious disease, as ye plague, pox measles or pestilent burning feaver or to remove any offencive or venimous water from ye harte or stomacke or to be used after a surfeite brin passions of ye mother or for Children in fitts of Convlsion or is generaly good to Comfort &amp; stranthen nature in all Cold Causes what soe Ever. Dr Matt; For ye faulling sickenes. Dr Matt For ye faulling sickenes A speciall good Saule Epon any suddaine occation or for any greene wounde. Dr Matt A water to wash a wounde bee fore dresing wth Sallve For ye hot goute &amp; weekenes in ye Backe. Dr Matt; The Jeroes plaister for a Consumption. Dr. Ford To heale an Issue For a paine or atch Coming of Cold or wett in ye Limbes. Dr. Matt A gentle purge for humors in ye Body To stope ye weeping of Sinewes; To Make ye Paraceleis Emplaster; A poultis for inflamation and seate in a Sore wound For ye dropsie purging of fleame or water A very good Saule to Ripen and Seale an impostume For an impostume &amp; paine in ye seade To open ye breast stomack wt fleame Causing Shortnes of breath or for ye Longs. Dr Matt; A Salve for all maner of wounds To Make ye plaster to ye saide wounde before Rehearsed For a Burne. Dr Matt A posset drinke for a feavor; A Comfortable Strenghing Jelly Oyntment of earth mose or earth Liver worte good for all weaknes in ye backe, hot gouts &amp; such like. Dr Matt An Exelent water for ye Stone; A very good oyle for wounds A speciall bath for ye winde Collicke ye stone &amp; other paines in ye Sides &amp; belly. Dr Matt For ye Coming out of ye fundament A water against any infection or in fectious matter to expell it from ye principall parts; A Speciall water for sore Eyes in man or horse A glister For a Cough For ye itching of ye Eyes &amp; to stay ye humor yt faleth into them. Dr Matt; For a Scaled Heade The water The oyntment An Exelent medicine for Convolsion fitts The greene pliaster For a fistula, an Exelent medicen; Unguentum Alablastrame A drinke for greene wounds fistulaus; or other Bruises A spetiall Seircloath to skin and heale; A Receipt of a drinke for a fistula For a bruis in ye Eye For a wound in ye Eye Sight To Make sirrope of grillow flowers; To Make an exelent drinke good for many in fermities; Especially for any greene sore or fassionable desease A Saule to draw &amp; heale A water for ye wormes; For the timpeny An Oyntment for ye Same Greefe A poultis for ye Same Greefe For a Cough of ye Lungs though ye deseas hath brought ye party to a great weakenes. L.M:b:C To breake draw &amp; heale a fellen If it bee taken in time; To Make Sperit of Mintes and Sperit of Wine To Make ye Red oyle for new wounds; To Make Sirrope of Voyolets For weake or shrunke or strayned sinewes. La: J:J: To Make oyle of earth wormes For Shrunke sinnewes For the Spleene very good; Lucattellos Balsome it is a good Saule for a greene wounde yt hath bin neglected for to draw &amp; heale a fellon after it is broken or for an ould sore after it is Clensed from Its fillthy flesh and venum A salve for a fellon For ye Collique in ye stomacke A Corasive for proud flesh in a sore; The Yellow Salve good for a sore Breast. Mrs. Hudson; To Make a healing salve or blark SeirCloath To distil worme wood water strong A salve for a Blast To Make ye butter plaster it will heale well For a peirle in ye Eye; To Cleans foule sores An other for ye Same An Oyntment for Inflamations To coole Infamations about sores A degestive salve; An exelent medicen for a swelen &amp; sore brest or a rhume in ye eyes wch wee call ye Kings evill ye brest must be keept warme and Cleane An exelent plaster for a sore Brest An exelent Eye water For A peirle in ye eye An other for ye Same To prevent a fellon if it be applied in time For a fellon; To Make sirrope of damaske Roses To Make Sirrope of any greene herbe To Make Sirrope of ye sower fruts Juyces as are Lemons; oringes Citoruns, Curranberrys &amp; pumgranats or unripe grapes To preserve Ellecompane Roots For a cough or any stoping in ye chest, Kidny or blader wth out ye Oyntment A most exelent medicen for scaldes, burnes or inflamations though wth gun poud or lighting For a bruse in ye body exelent; To Make a purging Apozema An oyntment for wormes A powder for ye wormes To take out fier &amp; beate back Inflamations To make concerue of damsons or pruens; For ye Rickets ye drinke The Oyntment An other Oyntment for ye Same A cape for ye fore saide desease it is to be woren wn you use ye oyntment &amp; drinke it is Allsoe good for Rhumes; To distill brume water or any other scarbe wth wine To drive spirits of spices or any other Aromaticall bodyas Rosemary &amp; Juniper For weeping sinnewes For a Cough For a Rhumetick stomacke For Eyes that have Red flesh; An exelent glister for ye stone in ye Kidneis. Dm Eli Bucly For ye Itch For a philme on ye Eye For ye Jaundes though farre Gon To stope ye Laske suddainely; For ye bitting of any venimus beast or any meaner poyson either eat or drunken For ye bitting of a mad dog For an old ousing sore For a tittar; For a scald head For a scabed head A bath to take ye Maligerety out of old sores; To Make a Cearecloath for Fontanells Pills for Fontanells To Make sirrope of Leomons or ye like fruites; For the Kings Evill To stope ye bleeding of an inward vaine yt is broken; A poultes to drawe &amp; cleans an Impostumation in ye flesh A poultes to asswage ye paine of the goute A purge for ye same To alay inflaymation in an Impostumation To Make sirrope Althea For ye melting of fatt inwardly by an over heat; A powder for ye greene sicknes For ye Hiccocks An Exelent water for winde in ye stomacke; For the Jaunders An other for ye same Hare powder fo ye stone and strangullian For an ague in ye head; An Opeing strengthening broath To clarify hony for sirropes For the dropsey For ye passion of ye heart An other for ye same A water for a fostula, though in A noes; Compound oyntment of Earth wormes for bruised or straind sinewes For ye Plague An opening drinke for a cough pthiseck or any stoping in ye brest For one yt cannot hold his water For ye Stone colligue; An Exellent medicen for an inward Impostume in ye body to betaken whilst it is gathering or after it is broken to cleans ye dregs from gathering againe To kill any itch yt coms of heat To make sirrop of Roses with Helebor To Make unguentum Egiptiatum; To make cibron water To make spiritt of Saffron To make Joccolet; To make an exelent water against Mallanehcolly A very good salve For ye falling sicknes For weake Lame Limbs To make unguentum album for common use For a dysines or dullnes in ye head; An Exelent moderate Cordiall to drive out ye small pox or ye Like infection To keepe ye small pox out of ye throat To keepe ye small pox out of ye Eyes To keepe ye small pox out of ye Nostrelles To Make ye small pox shell of Quirk whch prevents pitting For a squinsy or fallen Jawes; To cause sleepe though in childbed For a wasting weaknes in ye backe An other for ye same An other for ye same For ye gout To stay vomiting; For Eyes yt are sweld wth humors A gentle purging wth whey or ale if you like it better To breake an Impostim in ye head For an Impostim in ye head wn it is broken For griping in ye belly though in childbed For a sore yt runs &amp; will not heale To keepe teeth cleane &amp; good for those wth smell; A dry bath for ye gout or any Ache A pretious Eye water proved on a Man yt had lost his sight 10 yeares To stay a Laske in a young child For a bruis althoug it be cut For ye maw wormes To stay vomiting To disolve fleame at ye stomacke For ye rising of ye longs, though neere strangling; For ye falling sicknes in a child or fitts like it For ye frets in a childe For paine in ye head For one yt cannot make water For ye stone in ye blader For a child yt cannot Make water A Marmelate for swounding fainting &amp; dissines For ye spleene or any stich or deafnes For a Joynt Ague; To breake flegme in a young child though but one mounth old To stay bleeding at ye nose For the purple feavor A spetiall powder for ye memory &amp; the stomacke &amp; all ye vitalls A poultis to prevent ye breaking of a swelled leg To strengthen &amp; sharpen ye stomacke For ye running of ye Raines &amp; to knit bones; For ye falling sicknes For ye sceatica To procure sleepe; For a thrush in childs mouth or ye Like soarenes in any mouth or throat A posset drinke for ye stone For ye stone &amp; approved good to coole ye Raines A preservative against ye plague For a sweelling yt cometh wth a sprain or bruis A spetiall antidote against ye plague For to fetch out any creeping thing in ye Eare; For deafnes &amp; itching in ye eares A plaster for a rupture much Commend For ye stopage of urin by congealed bloud For sharfies of urin or ye like For ye wormes though far gon Rotten flesh or other ways To make oyle of whelps; An experemented good preseription for a flegmetigue ague or ye like opression of flegme in a child about 10 yeares old. Dr Smith A poultis to resist ye mortifying of a wound. J: C hand Drinke for a Rupture For deafnes &amp; to draw an Impostume For gidines or weaknes of ye head; To Make a drinke for winde To Make aqua cardicca To make pepper cakes for ye stomacke A cordiall water for surfits farnting and many stomacke Infirmityes A good Julip For ye filling out of ye fundament For one yt makes bloudy urin; An Exelent water to wash a sore or canker For a canker or any very soare throat For a sore throat though it be ulcerated For a canker; A singular medicen for wet canker or dry or any issue in any parte of mans body wch will not be healed wth salve, untell it be stayed, or for ye falling of ye uvula, or ye tooth ach yt cometh of Rhume A Exelent medicen for ye canker in ye mouth nose or body How to know a canker To heale a sore niple To knit cut scinewes; For ye falling sicknes An Exelent oyntment for ye dropsy Eye water for dim eyes For eyes that are neere Lost For lamnenes bruis or pain in ye feet For ye stopege of urin To bring wormes out of ye flesh; A most Exelent medicen for deseased horses it is ye best scouring yt can be given &amp; besides clearing ye body from all ill humors it is wonderfull feeding for in fouertene dayes taking it will make fatt &amp; so und ye leanest unsound horce yt can possibly be cured For ye dry cough &amp; ye Glaunders in horses For dry foundred horses For ye scratches of hors legs; To make the Angellot Cheesis; For ye fashons in a Ears For a galled hors backe A water for ye stone; A rasett to quel the wague To Make Saffron Bread To Make Orange Cream; To wash Cullered silke or gold work To feede chickens fat speedily For a beast yt cannot dung For a sicke pig or hog To make Corslipt wine; A receipt to make the best plague water
</summary>
            <textLang mainLang="" source="IANA">English</textLang>
            <msItem n="1" xml:id="MS_212_1">
              <author>Corbett, Arthur</author>
              <title type="original">Corbett, Arthur</title>
              <title type="standard"/>
              <textLang mainLang="" source="IANA">English</textLang>
              <filiation/>
              <filiation>Hashmarks (#) are used in the list of recipes to indicate where the indexers were unable to read the original text.</filiation>
            </msItem>
          </msContents>
          <physDesc>
            <objectDesc form="codex">
              <supportDesc material="">1 volume<extent>94 ll. folio. 30 x 19 cm. In vellum covers from a cut-down Deed of Sale, dated 1641. Margins and corners frayed.<dimensions type="leaf" unit="cm"><dim type="width"/><dim type="length"/></dimensions><dimensions type="written" unit="cm"><dim type="width"/><dim type="length"/></dimensions></extent><foliation/><collation/><condition><p/><p/><p/><p/></condition><support><watermark/></support></supportDesc>
              <layoutDesc>
                <layout writtenLines="">
                  <note/>
                </layout>
              </layoutDesc>
            </objectDesc>
            <handDesc>
              <handNote script=""/>
            </handDesc>
            <decoDesc>
              <decoNote type="marginal"/>
              <decoNote type="illustration"/>
            </decoDesc>
            <additions/>
            <bindingDesc>
              <binding>
                <p>94 ll. folio. 30 x 19 cm. In vellum covers from a cut-down Deed of Sale, dated 1641. Margins and corners frayed.</p>
              </binding>
            </bindingDesc>
          </physDesc>
          <history>
            <origin>
              <origDate>Middle 17th century</origDate>
            </origin>
            <provenance/>
            <acquisition>From the Coley Park Sale, January 1908, Lot 660.</acquisition>
            <acquisition type="accrual"/>
          </history>
          <additional>
            <adminInfo>
              <recordHist>
                <source>
                  <bibl>
                    <title>Catalogue of Western Manuscripts on Medicine and Science in the Wellcome Historical Medical Library</title>
                    <author>S. A. J. Moorat</author>
                    <placeName>London</placeName>
                    <publisher>Wellcome Institute for the History of Medicine</publisher>
                    <date>1962-1973</date>
                  </bibl>
                </source>
              </recordHist>
              <availability status="">
                <p/>
              </availability>
              <availability>
                <licence/>
              </availability>
              <custodialHist>
                <custEvent type="cataloguing">Database description transcribed from S.A.J. Moorat, [i]Catalogue of Western Manuscripts on Medicine and Science in the Wellcome Historical Medical Library[/i] (London: Wellcome Institute for the History of Medicine, 1962-1973).</custEvent>
                <custEvent type="exhibition"/>
                <custEvent type="digitised">Digitised: Yes</custEvent>
              </custodialHist>
            </adminInfo>
            <surrogates>In addition, a microfilm copy is held as AMS/MF/232.</surrogates>
            <surrogates/>
            <listBibl>
              <bibl>Published (in microfilm form) in [i]Women in Medicine: Remedy Books, 1533 - 1865[/i], ed. Sara Pennell (Woodbridge, Connecticut: Primary Source Microfilm, 2004).</bibl>
            </listBibl>
            <listBibl>
              <bibl/>
            </listBibl>
          </additional>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="LCSH">
          <bibl>
            <ref target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/about.html#lcsh">Library of Congress Subject Headings</ref>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="MeSH">
          <bibl>
            <ref target="">MeSH</ref>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#LCSH">
          <list>
            <item facs="">
              <term ref="subject_">
                <p>Medicine, Traditional</p>
              </term>
            </item>
            <item facs="">
              <term ref="subject_">
                <p>[p]Formulas, recipes, etc.</p>
              </term>
            </item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="#MeSH">
          <list>
            <item facs="">
              <term ref="subject_"/>
            </item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2026-05-05" who="Victoria Sloyan">Transformed Calm xml export to TEI xml file using a transformation scenario</change>
      <change when="" who="">Manual edits following automated Calm-TEI transformation</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
