<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="MS.169">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title/>
            <title type="collection">Wellcome Collection</title>
            <respStmt xml:id="SM">
               <resp when="1973">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>S. A. J. Moorat</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="RM">
               <resp>Calm encoder</resp>
               <persName>Macfarlr</persName>
               <note>08/10/2002</note>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="LS">
               <resp when="2026">TEI Encoder</resp>
               <persName>Lara Salha</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Wellcome Collection</publisher>
            <idno>UkLW</idno>
            <address>
               <orgName type="institution">Wellcome Collection</orgName>
               <street>215 Euston Rd</street>
               <settlement>London</settlement>
               <postCode>NW1 2BE</postCode>
            </address>
            <distributor>
               <email>library@wellcome.org</email>
            </distributor>
            <idno type="msID">MS.169</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <settlement>London</settlement>
                  <institution>Wellcome Collection</institution>
                  <repository>Wellcome Library</repository>
                  <idno type="shelfmark">Western MSS series 4 - Requestable</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="RefNo">
                     <idno>MS169</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier type="accession">
                     <idno>39158</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier type="Sierra">
                     <idno>b18900008</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <summary>A boke of hearbes and receipts.
                     
                     <p>The start of some of the folio have been transcribed as the following:</p>
                     <p>"The Vertues of sages"</p>
                     <p>"The temperature of minte"</p>
                     <p>"Of Pellitory of the walle, the temperatures"</p>
                     <p>"The temperature of wilde tyme The Vertues Of garden tyme/the nature of it The Vertues, cont. on folio 14"</p>
                     <p>"cont. from folio 13, Of garden tyme/the nature of it/This tyme is hot and drye in the third degree. The Vertues"</p>
                     <p>"cont. from folio 14, Of garden tyme/the nature of it/This tyme is hot and drye in the third degree. The Vertues The temperature and vertues of Hyssope"</p>
                     <p>"The temperature and vertues of Hedge Hyssop Thrtues"</p>
                     <p>"Of lavander spike, the temperature, ,the vertues, cont. on folio 18"</p>
                     <p>"cont. from folio 17, The vertues"</p>
                     <p>"The temperature of Bromell The vertues The vertues of dodder, cont. on folio 20"</p>
                     <p>"cont. from folio 19, The vertues of dodder"</p>
                     <p>"The temperature of Cowslips Vertues, cont. on folio 22"</p>
                     <p>"cont. from folio 21, Vertues"</p>
                     <p>"The temperature of butter Burre"</p>
                     <p>"The Temperature of rosemary The vertues, cont. on folio 26"</p>
                     <p>"cont. from folio 25, The vertues"</p>
                     <p>"The temperature of Harte toonge The vertues The temperature of Daues Roote, or Cranes bill The vertues, cont. on folio 28"</p>
                     <p>"cont. from folio 27, The vertues"</p>
                     <p>"The nature of Adders toong"</p>
                     <p>"The temperature of tormentill, or Potfoile The vertues"</p>
                     <p>"A soveraigne medicine for the payne and buzzinge in the head wich hindreth the hearinge An excellent medisine for acoutymall head ache Another for payne in the head "</p>
                     <p>"Allin in Englyhe garlicke or the poore mans Treakle it is verie sharpe, hote and dre in the fourthe degree. It exulcerateth the skyn by raising of blisters"</p>
                     <p>"The whyte garden lily is hote and ptly of a subtill substance, but the roote is drie in the first degree and hote in the second, cont. on folio 37"</p>
                     <p>"cont. from folio 37, The whyte garden lily is hote and ptly of a subtill substance, but the roote is drie in the first degree and hote in the second"</p>
                     <p>"Moonewort or madwort"</p>
                     <p>"Garden Lupyne"</p>
                     <p>"For a poultisse"</p>
                     <p>"A Sovaryne medicyne for any could ache, bruse or swelling, or wrenche whatsoever"</p>
                     <p>"A Purging Drinke to clense the lyver"</p>
                     <p>"For tremblinge of the harte A medicyne for the colicke and the Stoue A sovaryne glyter for the stov, cont. on folio 45"</p>
                     <p>"cont. from folio 44, A sovaryne glyter for the stov"</p>
                     <p>"A restoratyve broth to bring them that are weake feeble to their pfecte healthe agayne"</p>
                     <p>"A medicyne for the plague The kynge medicyne for the plague, cont. on folio 48"</p>
                     <p>"cont. from folio 47, The kynge medicyne for the plague"</p>
                     <p>"A speciall meanes to pr#hue health "</p>
                     <p>"Steps of Preserving The first receite how to clarifie yor suger"</p>
                     <p>"When to clarify sugar The second receite when to knowe your suger is in athin seruppe"</p>
                     <p>"The third receite howe to know when your suger is boyled to a full sirrupp The fourth receipte howe to knowe your sirrup is boiled to a manuus Christis height The fist receite howe to knowe when your sugar is at a randie height The sixt receite howe to knowe when your suger is at a castinge height "</p>
                     <p>"When your suger is Boiled to a Candie height A Receite howe to make diet bread toher waies called prince biskett"</p>
                     <p>"A Receite howe to make mackarones A Receite how to make Naples biskett"</p>
                     <p>"A Receite howe to make Cosquillians A receite howe to make almon cakes"</p>
                     <p>"A Receite howe to make White paste Royall A Receyte how to make Fyne Suger Cakes"</p>
                     <p>"A Receit how to make Red paste Royall A Receite how to make Red letter in Synamon paste A Receipte how to make Suger plate, cont. on folio 59"</p>
                     <p>"cont. from folio 58, A Receipte how to make Suger plate A Receipte how to make white mustardyue or Red A Receipte how to make a Marche payne"</p>
                     <p>"Another waie to make a marche payne A Receipte how to make a Noble feases A Receipte to make gentheleases, cont. on folio 61"</p>
                     <p>"cont. from folio 60, A Receipte to make gentheleases A receipte to make white Qindinie of pippins A Receipte to make red Quodinis of pippins, cont. on folio 62"</p>
                     <p>"cont. from folio 61, A Receipte to make red Quodinis of pippins A Receipte to prserve cherries Another Receipte to prserve Cheries, cont. on folio 63"</p>
                     <p>"cont. from folio 62, Another Receipte to prserve Cheries A Receipte how to Dry peares A Receipte to pserve A pricockes, cont. on folio 64"</p>
                     <p>"cont. from folio 63, A Receipte to pserve A pricockes A Receipte how to pserve Raspasses A receipte to prserve quynces whyte, cont. on folio 65"</p>
                     <p>"cont. from folio 64, A receipte to prserve quynces whyte A Receipte to pserve Quince Red Another Receipte to make quince Red, cont. on folio 66"</p>
                     <p>"cont. from folio 65, Another Receipte to make quince Red A Receipte to make whyte marmalad of Quynces A Receipte to make red marmalad of Quynce"</p>
                     <p>"A Receipte to make Marmalad of Quynce both smoth and Red A Receipte to make paste of Quince as they make it beyonde sea A Receipte to Pserve Damsons, cont. on folio 68"</p>
                     <p>"cont. from folio 67, A Receipte to Pserve Damsons A Receipte to make paste of Goosberies A Receipte to make paste of pipins, cont. on folio 69"</p>
                     <p>"cont. from folio 68, A Receipte to make paste of pipins"</p>
                     <p>"The tempature of St. Johns woorte The vertues"</p>
                     <p>"Te tempature and vertus of Buglasse"</p>
                     <p>"To make pfumes and ahalfe Aquamirabilis"</p>
                     <p>"The receipte to make rosasolis, cont. on folio 76"</p>
                     <p>"cont. from folio 75, The receipte to make rosasolis A soveraigne water Invented by Doctor Steeven"</p>
                     <p>"A Medecine for the same To make an other plaister for them that have coulde stomacks and full of winde, and with wilhringe the stomacke into pfect order of disgesture Another verie good one for the same, cont. on folio 78"</p>
                     <p>"cont. from folio 77, An other verie good one for the same A good medicine for the weakenes and couldnes of the stomacke"</p>
                     <p>"For the stoppinge of the stomacke or takinge therin coulde / an excellent medicine A medycyne for the strength nynge of the barke, cont. on folio 80"</p>
                     <p>"cont. from folio 79, A medycyne for the strength nynge of the barke"</p>
                  
                  </summary>
                  <textLang mainLang="">English</textLang>
                  <msItem n="1" xml:id="MS.169_1">
                     <author key="">Bulkeley, Elizabeth</author>
                     <title key="">Bulkeley, Elizabeth</title>
                     <textLang mainLang=""/>
                     <textLang otherLangs=""/>
                     <incipit>
                        <locus/>
                     </incipit>
                     <explicit>
                        <locus/>
                     </explicit>
                     <colophon>
                        <locus/>
                     </colophon>
                     <filiation/>
                     <note/>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="vellum">
                        <support/>
                        <extent>38 ll. 4to.
                           <dimensions unit="cm" type="leaf">
                              <dim type="diameter">152cm</dim>
                              <dim type="length">192cm</dim>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation/>
                        <collation>
                           <formula/>
                           <signatures/>
                        </collation>
                        <condition>Some margins and corners frayed.</condition>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote/>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <additions>
                     <p/>
                  </additions>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding>
                        <p>Modern vellum covers.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace>
                        <country/>,
                                        <region/>,
                                        <settlement/>,
                                        <orgName/>
                     </origPlace>
                     <origDate calendar="Gregorian">1627</origDate>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>From the Library of Mrs. Charles Elton [1838-1914].</provenance>
                  <acquisition>Purchased at Sotheby's 1/5/1916, Lot 82.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>
                           <bibl>
                              <title>Catalogue of Western Manuscripts on Medicine and Science in the Wellcome Historical Medical Library</title>
                              <author>S. A. J. Moorat</author>
                              <placeName>London</placeName>
                              <publisher>Wellcome Institute for the History of Medicine</publisher>
                              <date>1962-1973</date>
                           </bibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability status="free">
                        <p/>
                     </availability>
                     <custodialHist>
                        <custEvent/>
                     </custodialHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl type="microfilm">In addition, a microfilm copy is held as AMS/MF/232.</bibl>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl>
                     <head/>
                     <bibl/>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="LCSH">
               <bibl>
                  <ref target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/about.html#lcsh">Library of Congress Subject Headings</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="MeSH">
               <bibl>
                  <ref target="">MeSH</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#LCSH">
               <list>
                  <item facs="">
                     <term ref="subject_">
                        <p>Materia Medica Medicine, Traditional &lt;p&gt;Formulas, recipes, etc. Botany</p>
                     </term>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#MeSH">
               <list>
                  <item facs="">
                     <term ref="subject_"/>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>Sloyanv</change>
         <note>09/07/2025</note>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
