<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="MS.144">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="collection">Wellcome Collection</title>
            <respStmt xml:id="SM">
               <resp when="1973">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>S. A. J. Moorat</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="RM">
               <resp when="2002-10-08">
                  Calm encoder
                </resp>
               <name>Macfarlr</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="VS">
               <resp when="2026-01-06">TEI encoder</resp>
               <name>Sloyanv</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Wellcome Collection</publisher>
            <idno>UkLW</idno>
            <address>
               <orgName type="institution">Wellcome Collection</orgName>
               <street>215 Euston Rd</street>
               <settlement>London</settlement>
               <postCode>NW1 2BE</postCode>
            </address>
            <distributor>
               <email>library@wellcome.org</email>
            </distributor>
            <idno type="msID">MS.144</idno>
            <availability>
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <settlement>London</settlement>
                  <institution>Wellcome Collection</institution>
                  <repository>Wellcome Library</repository>
                  <idno>MS.144</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="accession">
                     <idno>75684</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier type="Sierra">
                     <idno>b19258124</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <summary>&lt;p&gt;A collection of medical, cookery and veterinary receipt, etc.</summary>
                  <textLang>English; Latin</textLang>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_1">
                     <title>Front cover</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_2">
                     <title>Inside front cover, library seal</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_3">
                     <title>Inside front cover</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_4">
                     <title>Booke of receites howe to make a sweet cake. For a potle of wine epecres. Perfumed pufes</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_5">
                     <title>To preserve quinces. To make marmelet</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_6">
                     <title>To preserve whit bulles or whit peare plomes. To preserve barberys</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_7">
                     <title>To preserve aprecottes. To preserve cheryes</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_8">
                     <title>To preserve goosbeery. Losenges of roses or flowers</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_9">
                     <title>To preserve oranges and leamonds</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_10">
                     <title>Sirope of Fimetary. Sirrope of vilolets</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_11">
                     <title>Sirope of clowgile flowers. Sirope of rasberyes. Sirope of orrenges ore Lemonds</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_12">
                     <title>To make mannes cristi</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_13">
                     <title>To make allmond Butter. To make whit leach</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_14">
                     <title>To make allmond flurerdeles. For a heghoge puden</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_15">
                     <title>Howe to make a lumber pye. Sawse for a shoulder of mutton</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_16">
                     <title>Sause for a shoulder of moton. To rost a shoulder of moton. To make sturgon of a tarkey. A stued lobster</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_17">
                     <title>Frid harty chocke. A fremhe dishe. A fremh dishe. A fride rabett. Sause of anchoves</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_18">
                     <title>Smaulde Sooles. Frid chichens. To peckelle oysters</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_19">
                     <title>For a boore</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_20">
                     <title>To make fine crackell cakes. Mis killegrew cakes</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_21">
                     <title>To make gingerbread of allmonds</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_22">
                     <title>To make very fine Biscute</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_23">
                     <title>To make Hydromel. To make mead</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_24">
                     <title>To make rosa solis or ros solis</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_25">
                     <title>To make treacle of herbes. For a coold stomacke cowld. An electuarie against malamolie</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_26">
                     <title>To stanche blood when the vaine is cutt. Another of ##r Groopes. Another. To stanche bleden att the nose. Another. Another</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_27">
                     <title>For the ruketts. A drinke for the same</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_28">
                     <title>Sirrup for the Rickets. For the scurvie a excellent dreinke</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_29">
                     <title>A receipt for the scurvy. Another. For the rickets. For convoltion fitts in a child. Good for the nurce</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_30">
                     <title>To prevent convoltion fitts. For convoltion fitts. A electuary good for convoltion fitts</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_31">
                     <title>To make one to sleape. For the rickets and consumtion</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_32">
                     <title>Medicine against the pectilence taught King Henry the Seventh. King Henry the Eight sent this to the Lord Mayor of London against the plague, cont. on folio 52</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_33">
                     <title>cont. from folio 51, King Henry the eight sent this to the Lord Mayor of London against the plague. For the plague in the guts in man</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_34">
                     <title>For a tetter. To skine a sore. For a canker in the mouth. Another. Another. For a straine or wrince. For a cutt or green wound</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_35">
                     <title>For the paulsies in the hands</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_36">
                     <title>For paine in the backe. Another</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_37">
                     <title>For spitting of blood. For any in the stomacke or infecttions truble. For the ianndice. Another for the yellow jaundice</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_38">
                     <title>To cause one to sleep. For the stone collick. For the worms</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_39">
                     <title>For paine in the teethe. For a sweet breath. A faire purgation</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_40">
                     <title>For the dropsce. Another. Good for the swelling in the body and leggs. For the blood clenesing after the measels or sprenge off scabes, cont. on folio 60</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_41">
                     <title>cont. from folio 59, To bring out the smale pox or measells. A great secret secret to cure a cough in 2 or 3 days. A precious watter for the eyes</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_42">
                     <title>A perfect and a proved good water to take away the spotts of the smalepoxe&lt;To make the face clean and fair and take awaye spotts. For the smale poxe and to bring them out</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_43">
                     <title>For the patient that have the small poxe. Electuary against looseneffe. Another for looseneffe and a could stomake. For the smale pox or swine pocks to bring them out. To cause one to sleep. To cause one to sleepe</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_44">
                     <title>A very good broath to comfort stomack and nurithe the body</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_45">
                     <title>For the wind of mother and convoltions fitts. For one thats trubled with winde and fleme</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_46">
                     <title>Most soueraine for wind</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_47">
                     <title>A very good water against Melamholy, cont. on folio 67</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_48">
                     <title>cont. from folio 66, A very good water against Melamholy</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_49">
                     <title>To still aqua vite. To make the best aqua composite. A very good aqua coposita to bee mixed with rosasolis cordiall and comfortable</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_50">
                     <title>Dotter Stenens water named aqua mirabila. Surfi# water to take att any time and after meales if anythinge afend the stomack</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_51">
                     <title>Dockter Butlers cordiall</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_52">
                     <title>For one that have a feveresh distemper</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_53">
                     <title>Lucatellus oyntment or balsamum Admirable for wounds</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_54">
                     <title>The vertues of Lucatellus oyntment or balsamum, cont. on folio 81</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_55">
                     <title>cont. from folio 80, The vertues of Lucatellus oyntment or balsamum, cont. on folio 82</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_56">
                     <title>cont. from folio 81, The vertues of Lucatellus oyntment or balsamum. A receite to keep a bruse from gangren never failem</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_57">
                     <title>To make the splene plaster in May</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_58">
                     <title>Pills for the stomack. The spleene pills. Creame of tarter one ounce. For the splene</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_59">
                     <title>A receipt for the grene sickenesse. The electuarie for the greene sickenesse, cont. on folio 87</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_60">
                     <title>cont. from folio 86, The electuarie for the greene sickenesse. The Third day purge. A powder for the winde</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_61">
                     <title>A receipt an excellent to cause the to bee loose and have constant stoles</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_62">
                     <title>Pills for the stomake</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_63">
                     <title>For a stufeing in the stomacke</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_64">
                     <title>A diett drinke to cleanse the Blood and stomack</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_65">
                     <title>For a Ruhms or Soreness in the Eyes. To Pickel Cucumbers and French Beans</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_66">
                     <title>A Receipt to make chesecakes</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_67">
                     <title>To pickel French Beans</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_68">
                     <title>To Make Currant Wine. To make a Burning Ointmet. To Make Green Goosebury wines. To make Cherry Marmalett</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_69">
                     <title>To Make Mead that Drinks like Sherry. Another To Make Mead</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_70">
                     <title>A Receipt for the Dropsy and scurvey prescribed by Docts Brosen of Norwich. To Pickel Walnuts Like Mangoes</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_71">
                     <title>A Receipt for Dressing of fish. A Receipt to Make Mead, cont. on folio 103</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_72">
                     <title>cont. from folio 99, A Receipt to Make Mead. To Make ginger bread, cont. on folio 103</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_73">
                     <title>Fricaoie of Rabits</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_74">
                     <title>back of folio 101</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_75">
                     <title>cont. from folio 100, To Make ginger bread</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_76">
                     <title>To Make Elder Wine</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_77">
                     <title>To Make a Cake</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_78">
                     <title>For a Cough. For a Cough</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_79">
                     <title>Cordiall Bitters. To make a Rabbit pye</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_80">
                     <title>Cordiall bitters. For a Consumption or Dropsye. Of milk Drink for a Hecktick fever. Me Shermans Purge</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_81">
                     <title>To Make Lemon Brandy. To make alamode Beef</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_82">
                     <title>To Collar Eles. To make a Sack-posset</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_83">
                     <title>To make Barly Cream. To make Jellys. To make an orange pudding, cont. on folio 112</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_84">
                     <title>cont. from folio 111, To make an orange pudding. To make a Triggary of Chickens or Rabbittes. To make Cows-lip-Wine</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_85">
                     <title>To make a Karrot-pudding. To make Scotch Collops</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_86">
                     <title>To Stew a Carp. To pott a Hare. Mead that was made for ### Doro Styleman February 1731. A #e#t to cure the Biting of a mad-Dog</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_87">
                     <title>To make almond [illegible] by Dr Hoiomans order. To make a brown Bread pudding</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_88">
                     <title>A Marrow Pudding. A rectfet for pain in the stomack</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_89">
                     <title>A Full discovery of the Medicines given by Ms Joanna Stevens for Cure of the stone and gravel. The powder is thus prepar'd, cont. on folio 118</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_90">
                     <title>cont. from folio 117, The powder is thus prepar'd. The pills ar thus prepared, cont. on folio 119</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_91">
                     <title>cont. from folio 118, The pills ar thus prepared. The Method of giving these Medicines are as follows, cont. on folio 120</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_92">
                     <title>cont. from folio 119, The Method of giving these Medicines are as follows</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_93">
                     <title>An approved receipt for the Cure or prevention of the Murrain in Cattle. To Make a cake. Lemon Pudding. Lemon Cream, cont. on folio 122</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_94">
                     <title>cont. from folio 121, Lemon Cream. To Make a Rice Pudding. To Make a Bread Pudding. To make Minie pyes</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_95">
                     <title>To make Water Vinegar. To make spice cakes. To pickle Mushrooms</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_96">
                     <title>To make Catchup. To make red Marmalade of Quinces, cont. on folio 125</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_97">
                     <title>cont. from folio 124, To make red Marmalade of Quinces. A Recipe for making Hessian Soup</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_98">
                     <title>For a felon</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_99">
                     <title>Dialectica ese ars bine differsndi</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_100">
                     <title>Bene, cont. on folio 132</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_101">
                     <title>cont. from folio 131, Bene. Eodemg# Sirsu logica dicta est. Inventio est prima pars Bialectica de invemendis argumentis &amp;c # Inuentio est. Pars Bialectica. Prima. De argumentis, cont. on folio 133</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_102">
                     <title>cont. from folio 132, De argumentis. Inrimendis. Argumentu est quodad aliquid argumendu est affectum est etc. Quod. Affectum est. Ad Arguendu. Aliquid. Ratio est in omnibus, cont. on folio 134</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_103">
                     <title>cont. from folio 133, Ratio est in omnibus. Actus est in omnibus. Existentia est in omnibus. Time non existit nisi in ve. Time non potest separati a rebus. Quales sant singula rationes sold st#se #siderata. singuld rationes affect## sunt ad argumendu. Gold. Per se. Argumentu est artificiale and in artificiale&lt;Artificiale prius in artificiale. Argu artificiale est. Quod ex se arguit. Artif est primu vel a primo or#l#, cont. on folio 135</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_104">
                     <title>cont. from folio 134, Artif est prima vel a primo or#l#. Prima est Quod est sud originis. Prima # artif originale ue# primogenea. Primum es absolution aut comparatam. Prima absoluta # Quod absolute a#gui#</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_105">
                     <title>A drinke for a sicke horse. To prevent the murrain</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_106">
                     <title>For any straine or stiffeling of a horse. For a horse that have Scaby heeles. For the gravelling of a horse in the foot. For the murrain in cows # and in and such catle. To prevent the murrain. For the murrain in pigs</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_107">
                     <title>For the could in the lungs or stomack of a horse. For a horse that is broken winded. For the farcy or by some called the farcion in a horse. For a strain in the pastorn ioyut</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_108">
                     <title>For the plague in the guts of horses. For the staggers and yellows. For the scratches. For the bots. For bots and worms</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_109">
                     <title>inside back cover</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_110">
                     <title>back cover</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.144_111">
                     <title>spine</title>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc>
                     <supportDesc>
                        <extent>7 bl ll. + 87 ff. + 26 ll. + 97 bl. ll. + 5 bl. ll. 8vo. A number of leaves have been cut out.<dimensions unit="mm">
                              <dim type="diameter">11</dim>
                              <dim type="length">16</dim>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation/>
                        <collation>
                           <formula/>
                           <signatures/>
                        </collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout/>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote>: mainly by two hands, one c. 1650, the other dated 1731-1739. &lt;p&gt;The original hand is that of ff. 1-82, of which ff. 1-38 are cookery receipts and the remainder medical. 
                        It also appears on 7 pp. at the end, containing veterinary receipts. &lt;p&gt;At the end also are 11 pp. headed 'Dialectica est ars bene disserendi', partly in English and partly in Latin, 
                        by a different hand, also c. 1650.</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding>
                        <p>Original vellum gilt binding defective, both clasps wanting.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate>c.1650-1739</origDate>
                  </origin>
                  <acquisition>Purchased 1931.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>
                           <bibl>
                              <title>Catalogue of Western Manuscripts on Medicine and Science in the Wellcome Historical Medical Library</title>
                              <author>S. A. J. Moorat</author>
                              <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                              <publisher>Wellcome Institute for the History of Medicine</publisher>
                              <date>1962-1973</date>
                           </bibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl type="microfilm">In addition, a microfilm copy is held as AMS/MF/232.</bibl>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>Published (in microfilm form) in &lt;i&gt;Women in Medicine: Remedy Books, 1533 - 1865&lt;/i&gt;, ed. Sara Pennell (Woodbridge, Connecticut: Primary Source Microfilm, 2004).</bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="LCSH">
               <bibl>
                  <ref target="https://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects.html">Library of Congress Subject Headings</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="MeSH">
               <bibl>
                  <ref target="https://meshb.nlm.nih.gov/search">MeSH</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#LCSH">
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <term>&lt;p&gt;Rhetoric</term>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <term>&lt;p&gt;Formulas, recipes, etc.</term>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <term>&lt;p&gt;Formulas, recipes, etc.</term>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#MeSH">
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <term>Veterinary Medicine</term>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <term>Cooking</term>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <term>Medicine, Traditional</term>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2026-01-06">Manual edits done by VS after XML transformation scenario</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
