<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="MS.1795">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="collection">Wellcome Collection</title>
            <respStmt xml:id="SM">
               <resp when="1973">Cataloguer</resp>
               <persName>S. A. J. Moorat</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="RM">
               <resp when="2002-10-08">
                  Calm encoder
                </resp>
               <persName>Macfarlr</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="VS">
               <resp when="2026-01-09">TEI encoder</resp>
               <persName>Sloyanv</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Wellcome Collection</publisher>
            <idno>UkLW</idno>
            <address>
               <orgName type="institution">Wellcome Collection</orgName>
               <street>215 Euston Rd</street>
               <settlement>London</settlement>
               <postCode>NW1 2BE</postCode>
            </address>
            <distributor>
               <email>library@wellcome.org</email>
            </distributor>
            <idno type="msID">MS.1795</idno>
            <availability>
               <p/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <settlement>London</settlement>
                  <institution>Wellcome Collection</institution>
                  <repository>Wellcome Library</repository>
                  <idno>MS.1795</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="accession">
                     <idno>78823</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier type="Sierra">
                     <idno>b18763728</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <summary>&lt;p&gt;Collection of cookery receipts, with some medical and veterinary receipts: by various hands. &lt;p&gt;Most of the medical and veterinary receipts are at the end of the volume.</summary>
                  <textLang>English</textLang>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_1">
                     <title>front cover</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_2">
                     <title>inside front cover, library stamp</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_3">
                     <title>index of recipes, cont. on folio 6</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_4">
                     <title>loose page, [Untitled]</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_5">
                     <title>cont. from folio 4, index of recipes, cont. on folio 7</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_6">
                     <title>cont. from folio 6, index of recipes, cont. on folio 8</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_7">
                     <title>cont. from folio 7, index of recipes, cont. on folio 9</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_8">
                     <title>cont. from folio 8, index of recipes, cont. on folio 10</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_9">
                     <title>cont. from folio 9, index of recipes, cont. on folio 11</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_10">
                     <title>cont. from folio 10, index of recipes</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_11">
                     <title>To Pickle Broomebudds, cont. on folio 17</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_12">
                     <title>cont. from folio 16, To Pickle Broomebudds. To make Lemon Creame. To make an Orange Pudding. To make Minced Pyes, cont. on folio 18</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_13">
                     <title>cont. from folio 17, To make Minced Pyes. To make white oatmell Puddings. To Frigasee A Rabitt. To make o# Leg of Lamb in ##oise meat. To make A Westplalia ham, cont. on folio 19</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_14">
                     <title>cont. from folio 18, To make A Westplalia ham. To make hartshorne Jelley. A good mixture of spices. To pot venison or Beafe</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_15">
                     <title>To make Angelott Cheese. To Roast A Rump of Beefe. To drye English Bacon Like Westphalia Lamb, cont. on folio 21</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_16">
                     <title>cont. from folio 20, To drye English Bacon Like Westphalia Lamb. To Stew A Rump of Beefe. To make Sugar Cakes. To make Marchpane. To make knotts wth Almonds, cont. on folio 22</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_17">
                     <title>cont. from folio 21, To make knotts wth Almonds. To make Cheese cakes. To Make Biskett, cont. on folio 23</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_18">
                     <title>cont. from folio 22, To Make Biskett. To Boyle A Sammon. To Boyle A Carpe wth ye black sauce. To make an Oatmeale pudding. To make Cheese Cakes. How to make Pancakes, cont. on folio 24</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_19">
                     <title>cont. from folio 23, How to make Pancakes. A Receipt of baked meates. To Make an Orange Pudding. To Make an apple pudding. To make Cowslip tansey, cont. on folio 25</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_20">
                     <title>cont. from folio 24, To make Cowslip tansey. To make Fritters. To make Puffes. To boyle A Codds head</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_21">
                     <title>To Roast A Shoulder of Mutton. To Stew A Knockle of veale. To drye Clarry and eggs. To make Wiggs. To Make A Goose pye</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_22">
                     <title>To Make Sasages of beefe att any time of the yeare. To make french Bread. A Medicine for A quinsey an Imposthume in ye throat or Allmonds. To pott an hare, cont. on folio 28</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_23">
                     <title>cont. from folio 27, To pott an hare. A Boyled Bread pudding. To Stuff A Shoulder of Mutton. The Sauce for it. To Stew A dish of Pippins</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_24">
                     <title>To Make Cheese Cakes. To Make A Goosberry Fooll. To Make Wild Cordes</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_25">
                     <title>To Make the King's Cakes</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_26">
                     <title>To Make Meate puddings. To Make A Goosberry Fool. To Make Ginger bread. To Make Custards</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_27">
                     <title>To Pickle Quinces. To Make A venison Pastie. To Make A Lemmon Pudding. To Make Excellent Cheese Cakes</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_28">
                     <title>To make Pound Cakes. To Pickle Oysters. To Make An Artichoake Pye</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_29">
                     <title>To Frye Artichoake Bottoms. To Stew Calves feete. To Make Lynks. To Make Appel Creame, cont. on folio 35</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_30">
                     <title>cont. from folio 34, To Make Appel Creame. To Make Sacke Creame. To Make Barley Creame. To Make Hartshorne Flummery. To Make Sugar Cakes</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_31">
                     <title>To Pickle Large Cowcumbers. To Bake Veales Tonnges. My Cosen Marshalls way of brewing, cont. on folio 37</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_32">
                     <title>cont. from folio 36, My Cosen Marshalls way of brewing. To Make Oyster Loaves. To Make Goosberry Vineger, cont. on folio 38</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_33">
                     <title>cont. from folio 37, To Make Goosberry Vineger. To Make Oyster Sasages. A Receipt to pickle Pidgeons. To prevent Fish from Tasteing Muddy. To make a Rice pudding. To make Westphalia Ham</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_34">
                     <title>To boyl an Ham. To Dry Mushrooms. The Queens Pudding. To Pickle herrings</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_35">
                     <title>To Pickle Peaches. To Dry Artichoak's Bottoms. To make Blanemanger. To make Jelly of Hartshorne</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_36">
                     <title>To make Jelly of Hartshorne. To make Scotch Collops. To make Chease cakes. To make Chease Cakes</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_37">
                     <title>The Past. To pott Beafe. To make Soope</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_38">
                     <title>Onion Soop. Soop Meigre. To make Almond Cheescakes. To make Blauemangse</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_39">
                     <title>To Make Mead. Harts Horn Flumery. To Pott a Tongue. Raison Wine</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_40">
                     <title>To make a Trifle. To Stew a Loin of Mutton. To make Rice Milk. To Dress Hoggs Fat &amp; Ears A La Mode De Pans. To make Shrub. Robn. Wrenn, cont. on folio 46</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_41">
                     <title>cont. from folio 45, To make Shrub. Robn. Wrenn. To Cure Ropy Beer</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_42">
                     <title>To make a Carraway Cake</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_43">
                     <title>To make A Pudding to cure Love</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_44">
                     <title>To make Apricock Wine. Another Receipt of Apricocke wine</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_45">
                     <title>To make Apricoke Wine. The Apricoke you may put into A candyed Sirrup then take them out and dry them it is a pretty Sweete meate. To Make strong mead. To make Currant Wine</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_46">
                     <title>To make Burch Wine. To make Cherry wine. To make Currant wine. To make Rasberry Wine. Another of Rasberrys, cont. on folio 54</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_47">
                     <title>cont. from folio 53, Another of Rasberrys. To Make Orange Wine. To Make Elder Wine</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_48">
                     <title>To Make Cowslip wine. To make Sider. To Make Quins Wine. To Make Small Mead. Frontiniae Wine</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_49">
                     <title>To make Jelly of Currants. To make Sweet Lemon cakes</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_50">
                     <title>To Make Cleare Cakes of Goosberrys Currants Damsons &amp; Rasberrys. To Make Jumballs or thin Cakes. To Make Lemon Creame Whipped. To Make Orange Cakes. To Make Quince Jumballs, cont. on folio 59</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_51">
                     <title>cont. from folio 58, To Make Quince Jumballs. To Make Quince Puffes. To Make Conserve of violetts. To preserve Goosberryes. To Make Orange or Lemon Puffes</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_52">
                     <title>To Make Paste of Barberries. To Preserve Damsons. To preserve White Peare Plumbs. To Preserve Apricockes White, cont. on folio 61</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_53">
                     <title>cont. from folio 60, To Preserve Apricockes White. To Make A Christiall Jelley. To Preserve Pippins Greene. To Make Paste of Plumms. To know how to Clarifie Sugar. To know when it is full Sirropp. To know when it is Candy Heigth. To know when it is Casting Heigth</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_54">
                     <title>To Make Green Goosberrie Cakes. To Drye Plumbs. To make sugar Cakes</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_55">
                     <title>To Dry Damsons. To preserve Apricocks or Malicatoones dry</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_56">
                     <title>A Receipt for Gout &amp; Rheumatism. An Excellent Bitter Draught. A Receipt for Strains &amp; Bruises in Horses. To Cure the Gease in Horses. A Cure for an ague</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_57">
                     <title>For a Serophulous Humour. To make Cock Broth. To make Sallub or Salope. The great Restorative for a Decay. To Cure the Inflammation of a Blister. Dr. Jeb's Receipt for Intermit ###</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_58">
                     <title>To Prevent miscarrying. the Lintseed Poultice excellent in any Bruise Hurt or Swelling either in man or Horse. For a Lingring &amp; Lurking Fever. An Infallible Cure for an ague</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_59">
                     <title>An eye Water for a hot Rheum for Horses. Tooth Powder, Mrs Smthers. Receipt for a Sore Mouth. For To Cure Blindness in Horses Eyes. For a Hectick Feaver in a Child</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_60">
                     <title>cont. from folio 71, The Universial Drops. Eye Water. To make good Ink. For the Piles When Inward</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_61">
                     <title>Dr Jebb for Shortness of Breath. The Tinctura Antiphthisica of Fuller. The Universial Drops, cont. on folio 70</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_62">
                     <title>Medicines for severall Diseases. A Receipt for a Cold. To make sweet Watter. A Remedy for the Tooth Acke</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_63">
                     <title>Dr. Levetts Bitter Draught. Dr Levetts Steel Wine. Mr. Fowlers receipt for the Scurvy. A Drink for the Scurvy. For a Dropsicall humour</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_64">
                     <title>A Conserve for a Cough. A syrrup good for shortness of breath, &amp; ye Assmah, &amp; Lunges. For Wormes in the Face. A Glyster for the Collick. Dr Howes Bitter Drops</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_65">
                     <title>cont. from folio 76, A Receipt for a Sinew Straine or Straine in the Loyns of an horse. For the Rheumatism. A Balsamick surrup for a Cough</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_66">
                     <title>cont. from folio 77, To make the pills to purge with ye Sage Drink. An oyntment for ye pills. To Kill rats. T cure ye Yellow Jaundice. A Drink for ye Kings Evill. A Receipt for a Sinew Straine or Straine in the Loyns of an horse, cont. on folio 75</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_67">
                     <title>To make a sage Drink for Women to be Fruitfull. To make the pills to purge with ye Sage Drink, cont. on folio 76</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_68">
                     <title>cont. from folio 79, A Receipt for the Kings Evill. To Joyne Broken Cheane##. A Receipt for an Ague. Doct. Lowers Directions to make the Tincture called Peters Elixir to be put up in pint or halfe pint bottles. A Receipt for the Collick or other illnesse in the stomach. A Reseipt for the Toothach. A shorter receipt for ye Tooth Ach</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_69">
                     <title>For the Itch. Dr. Hobses Receipt For the Kings Evill. A Receipt for the Kings Evill, cont. on folio 78</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_70">
                     <title>A Receipt for strains or Bruises in Horses, cont. on folio 81</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_71">
                     <title>cont. from folio 80, A Receipt for strains or Bruises in Horses</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_72">
                     <title>For Gout &amp; Rheumatism</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_73">
                     <title>A receipt for the Gout or Rheumatism</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_74">
                     <title>Dr Yardly directions for the Piles wth a Loosness. Mrs. Gees diat drinke for wind. Mrs Gees diat drink for the Stone in the Kidneys. Mrs Chilcorks Recaipt for the Ricketts A drink and Pouder. The Drink. The Pouder</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_75">
                     <title>For the small pox being struck in or any destemper that suddenly Infects the blould, or for ye biting of a mad dog. Mrs Lowards medicine for the Headach. Dr Boys his Receipt for ye Cialybat Wine. Dr Boys Bitter Draught. Dr. Boys Glyster for the Stone Colick</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_76">
                     <title>To Make Ratafia. An Excellent Purge for ye Head by doctor Carters Direccons. For a blow on the Eye. A snail watter for a Consumption. A powder for the Piles</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_77">
                     <title>To drye up the small pox. To Make Usquebaugh. To Make Hirapichra</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_78">
                     <title>cont. from folio 89, To Make ye searecloth for ye Breast. An Oyntment for ye Small Pox. My Lady Sydenhams Oyntment for ye Small pox. To Dry up the Small Pox</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_79">
                     <title>cont. from folio 90, A Cordiall water for any infectious disease an ye Plague pestilence burneing feaver Pox &amp; to remove any offensive water from ye stomacke especially after A surfeit good to be given to women in passions of the Mother &amp; to Children in Convulsion fitts it is usually given warme to Comfort wth all. Doctor Dentons Vomitt. To Make A Poultice for ye Breast. To Make ye searecloth for ye Breast, cont. on folio 88</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_80">
                     <title>cont. from folio 91,The Greene oyntmt for ye spleen Aches bruises straines swellings or palseys Comforting of ye sinewes &amp; bones. A seare Cloth. For A Consumpion Cough. To make Lucke tellub Balsame. A Cordiall water for any infectious disease an ye Plague pestilence burneing feaver Pox &amp; to remove any offensive water from ye stomacke especially after A surfeit good to be given to women in passions of the Mother &amp; to Children in Convulsion fitts it is usually given warme to Comfort wth all, cont. on folio 89</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_81">
                     <title>To Black frames or any other thing in Oyle to be shineing Color. To fetch out staines out of Linen. A medicine for a quinsey an imposthume in the throat or Alemonds. A Cure for any Canker or Mislity in ye mouth. The Greene oyntmt for ye spleen Aches bruises straines swellings or palseys Comforting of ye sinewes &amp; bones, cont. on folio 91</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_82">
                     <title>cont. from folio 93, To make Drinke for ye Kings Evill. For ye Itch. A Salve good to heale any soare cutt or Bruise. It is good for all Burne alsoe. For A Dropsie or Festulowe. For the scurvy &amp; paine in ye Leggs. An approved receipt ag ye stone. Glew for Black Frames</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_83">
                     <title>cont. from folio 94, To make Ballis Oyle. Glew for Black Frames. Oyle of Earthwormes &amp; Swallowes. A Receipt for ye Pleurisie or any pains ye side. To make the bitter Drinke. To make Liquid Laudanum. To make Drinke for ye Kings Evill, cont. on folio 92</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_84">
                     <title>cont. from folio 95, The Receipt of ye Gout Water. To make Cherry Water. To make Cinamond Water. An approved Frownse Water for a sore mouth or any Kind of Wound or Canker in ye mouth. An Excellent salve wch is good to use wth ye Frownse water if it bee a great Wound or else ye water will cure of itt Selfe. Oyle of Swallows to releive straynings of sinews &amp; old Bruises. To make Ballis Oyle, cont. on folio 93</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_85">
                     <title>cont. from folio 96, To make Orange Water. Palsie Water. A Cordiall Water. The Receipt of ye Gout Water, cont. on folio 94</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_86">
                     <title>cont. from folio 97, For the Piles. The Receipt of ye Gout Water. The Dutches of Portsmouth's Water. Milke Surfeit Water. To make Poppy Water. Plain Mint Water. To Distill speere Mint Water. To make Angelico Water. To make Orange Water, cont. on folio 95</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_87">
                     <title>A Gentle Purge for A man. An Ointment good for all Burnes &amp; Scalds. A Exsent Remedy for a bruise or straine. Elixir Salutcus for Cholick Gravell in ye Kidneys griping of ye Gutts &amp; Colds. For the Piles, cont. on folio 96</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_88">
                     <title>inner back cover</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_89">
                     <title>back cover</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS.1795_90">
                     <title>spine, Ancient Cookery &amp; Medical Receipts</title>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc>
                     <supportDesc>
                        <extent>12 ll. last 4 bl.. + pp. 11-278 + 53 bl. ll. + 29 ll. last bl.. 4to.
                           <dimensions unit="mm">
                              <dim type="diameter">151.2</dim>
                              <dim type="length">191.2</dim>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation/>
                        <collation>
                           <formula/>
                           <signatures/>
                        </collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout>Pp. 1-10, 27/28, 33-36, 57/58 are wanting. P. 196 is doubled in the pagination.</layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding>
                        <p>Modern buckram binding.</p>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate>c.1685-c.1725</origDate>
                  </origin>
                  <acquisition>Purchased 1932.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>
                           <bibl>
                              <title>Catalogue of Western Manuscripts on Medicine and Science in the Wellcome Historical Medical Library</title>
                              <author>S. A. J. Moorat</author>
                              <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                              <publisher>Wellcome Institute for the History of Medicine</publisher>
                              <date>1962-1973</date>
                           </bibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl type="microfilm">In addition, a microfilm copy is held as AMS/MF/225.</bibl>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl/>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="LCSH">
               <bibl>
                  <ref target="https://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects.html">Library of Congress Subject Headings</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="MeSH">
               <bibl>
                  <ref target="https://meshb.nlm.nih.gov/search">MeSH</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#LCSH">
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <term>&lt;p&gt;Formulas, recipes, etc.</term>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#MeSH">
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <term>Medicine, Traditional</term>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <term>Cooking</term>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <term>Veterinary Medicine</term>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2026-01-09">Manual edits done by VS after XML transformation scenario</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
